<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rejoynder to Mr. Wills, his Vindiciæ wherein the antiquity for believers and novelty of infant baptism is further confirmed : as also his groundless appeal distinctly answer'd, and the forgeries and mistakes boasted of, still found to be his own : with an appeal to his conscience about the same / by H. Danvers.</title>
            <author>Danvers, Henry, d. 1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D227</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13108986</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13108986</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21030)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 413:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rejoynder to Mr. Wills, his Vindiciæ wherein the antiquity for believers and novelty of infant baptism is further confirmed : as also his groundless appeal distinctly answer'd, and the forgeries and mistakes boasted of, still found to be his own : with an appeal to his conscience about the same / by H. Danvers.</title>
                  <author>Danvers, Henry, d. 1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 77, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Appears also in: Second reply in defence of the treatise of baptism. 1675.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wills, Obed. --  Vindiciae vindiciarum.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:2"/>
            <p>A REJOYNDER to Mr. WILLS his <hi>Vindiciae:</hi> Wherein The Antiquity for Believers, and Novelty of <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is further confirmed.</p>
            <p>As alſo, His groundleſs Appeal diſtinctly anſwer'd, and the Forgeries and Miſtakes boaſted of, ſtill found to be his own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With an Appeal to his Conſcience about the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the words of</hi> Tertulian <hi>and</hi> Nazianzen <hi>ſhew it was long before all were agreed of the time or Neceſſity of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Infants before the uſe of Reaſon, in caſe they were like to live to Maturity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>It was thought leſs needful to give it</hi> [viz. Infants Baptiſm,] <hi>a particular expreſs mention in the Records and Hiſtory of the Church [viz.</hi> In thoſe times] <hi>Mr.</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>in his</hi> More Proofs, <hi>p.</hi> 279.</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. Danvers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 5.11.</hi>
               </bibl> And ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my names ſake.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 16.10.</hi>
               </bibl> They have gaped upon me with their mouths, and have ſmote me upon the cheek reproachfully.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 119.42.</hi>
               </bibl> I ſhall have wherewithal to anſwer him that reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, for I truſt in thy word.</q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Caſtle,</hi> near the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:3"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>BEfore I had finiſhed with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> I was firſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted by a new adverſary, one Mr. <hi>Whitſton,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by my old Antagoniſt Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> not ſuffering me ſcarce to take breath, and three to one you know is odds. But hearing, that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> a meer ſtranger to me, had undertaken Mr. <hi>Whitſton,</hi> I have obtained ſo much leaſure, to conſider what our <hi>3d. Triumvir</hi> hath further to ſay to me. And whom I find upon a ſerious peruſal inſtead of giving that due ſatisfaction, my ſober <hi>Reply,</hi> (and all good men) might expect from him, for his manifold detected errors in Antiquity, abuſe of Authors, ſcurrility and indignity to my perſon (a meer ſtranger to him) injurious reproaches to the whole party of Baptiſts, (as well in this as other Nations; not only loading the profeſſors thereof with his ſlanders, but the profeſſion it ſelf, as leading to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy and Immorality) is pleaſed notwithſtanding to come forth in this wrathful, ſelf-juſtifying, and revengeful Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, abounding ſtill in his repeated and renewed errors and reproaches; as though an impenitent ſtanding by error was the beſt way to defend truth, and to recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate others, the faireſt way to clear himſelf, juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Malefactor, who fell foul upon his Proſecutor, Judge, Jury, and Witneſſes, as the beſt way to ſave himſelf: And with the Chaced Fox, raiſeth a Duſt to make his eſcape. Dealing juſt with me; as the Heathens did with the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of old, putting them into Bears Skins, and then ſet the Dogs upon them; or as the Papiſts have done with worthy Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> for detecting their errors and cruelties, have decry'd him as ſuch a Forger, that none ought to converſe with him. But Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> will find himſelf under a diſappointment, truth is not ſo to be baffled, nor innocency foil'd, he will yet meet with a
<pb facs="tcp:199364:4"/> Vindication of both, in his farther juſt detection and reproof.</p>
            <p>Theſe few Pages therefore do firſt truly diſcover to you, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great noiſe and clamour of miſtakes, that the queſtion diſcourſed betwixt us is certainly loſt, and given up by him, and that the Antiquity ſo much boaſted of is wholly for Believers, not Infants Baptiſm. With a ſerious and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Anſwer to his groundleſs frivolous Appeal; diſcovering withall, that he is truly guilty of thoſe crimes, and many more, that he would ſo injuriouſly father upon me, though what he diſcovers to have been my errors, I fully own, which are few, and very inconſiderable, miſtaking <hi>2</hi> or <hi>3</hi> names one for an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, viz. <hi>Aquinas</hi> for <hi>Albertus, Sericius</hi> for <hi>Hincmarus,</hi> not hitting a Popes Name, and not taking <hi>Walden</hi> to ſo good advantage as I ought for myſelf; that of <hi>Lanfrank</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich are all, of any weight, that I know of, none. of them hurting us in the leaſt, and and are ſo frivolous, that an ingenious man would ſcorn to have mentioned, much leſs to have made ſuch a duſt about.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time I muſt acknowledge, it is very ſad the World ſhould be troubled with ſuch ſtuff, as though ſuch accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, recriminations, and diſcovery of nakedneſs, was for their edification, which I can truly ſay is very grieving to me, and were not the truth of God likely to ſuffer by my ſilence, I ſhould rather have born his reproaches and ſlanders, than have made any return to him. And therefore what I have done on my part to prevent ſuch miſchiefs and inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, I think will be neceſſary to give you ſome particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of, having before only given you a hint thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> how much I have endeavoured with Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> to rectifie miſtakes, and miſ-underſtandings in a more Private, Friendly, Chriſtian way, that we might ſave the world this unneceſsary trouble.</p>
            <p>Know therefore, that my firſt Treatiſe of Baptiſm, having ſlept about <hi>12</hi> Months without any publick notice, and being ready to come forth with a <hi>2d.</hi> Edition, I improved my utmoſt
<pb facs="tcp:199364:4"/> intereſt with all ſorts, to procure what Objections did ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally lye againſt it, that if I had committed any miſtakes, I might rectifie them, having been conſtrained to take ſeveral things upon Truſt, for want of opportunity to examine them by their Originals: And therefore did Apologize in my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face for Candor, that if by the multitude of Quotations through ſo ancient a Track, they might find any particular miſtake, miſ-quotation, or miſ-applicatoon, they would not ſo dwell or inſiſt upon it, as to reject the truth of all the reſt, that are full, and clear, and without exception, the way that Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Sophiſters take, and the Method that Papiſts have all along taken in Reply to our Proteſtant Writers, though did aſſure, (and ſo I can ſay with a good Conſcience) that I have not willingly given any ſuch occaſion, and truly at laſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the malicious ſcrutiny, clamour and noiſe that has been made, it is matter of Admiration, that no more has been brought forth: Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> having diſcovered but thoſe few before mentioned: Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> but one that had any ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy: And Mr. <hi>Whitſton</hi> not one.</p>
            <p>Therefore hearing, That Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had ſomething to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, I ventured, as I have told you, to ſend to him; and underſtanding, that Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> had ſpent ſome time in the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Library, to trace my Authorities, and found me tardy in many, I ſent Two or Three Meſſages to him, to admit of ſome Converſe about it, but in vain; then upon the coming forth of the <hi>2d.</hi> Impreſſion, I ſent Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> one of them, with this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Underſtand you have ſome Exceptions againſt my Treatiſe of Baptiſm, eſpecially the Hiſtorical Part, and particularly about the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and that you intend ſpeedily to print the ſame. I having, <hi>Sir,</hi> printed a 2d. Impreſſion, and therein made ſome alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and very conſiderable additions, eſpecially as to the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes,</hi> have taken upon me the confidence to ſend you one; and which if it may tend to your ſatisfaction, may ſave the world, your ſelf, and me, the further trouble of Anſwers and Rejoynders, if not, if you will pleaſe to Communicate where your principal
<pb facs="tcp:199364:5"/> Objection lies, either to that, or any thing elſe, and admit of the Exchange of a Letter or Two about it; it may not be unſerviceable to the Truth, with this aſſurance, that if it may appear, that I have done any manifeſt injury to truth, I ſhall be ready to give the moſt publick ſatisfaction it may call for; it having been my earneſt and importunate deſire, ever ſince the Expoſure of the firſt, to procure any rational Objection againſt any thing I had ſaid, and which ſhould have been as wellcome to me as an Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, (becauſe it is only truth in ſincerity I deſign to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate) but do aſſure you, have not as yet met with the leaſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection from any one that I had not before obviated. And indeed as to the Hiſtorical Part, though it is not offered for proof, but illuſtration only, would be too great folly to render any willful miſtake, which every Scholar in his Library confutes; Which with the render of Chriſtian Reſpects, is recommended to your Conſideration, by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your unknown Friend and Servant, <hi>H. D.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>March</hi> 22. 1673.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To which Letter upon the 10th of <hi>May 1674.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> returns me anſwer, that had not my Letter come too late, it would have been incivility not to have complied with me; but that part of his Book was in the Preſs before mine came to his hand, and therefore deſired my excuſe, and not to reckon him a willing diſturber of the world, having never before invaded the Preſs.</p>
            <p>As though my Meſſages ſent to him (by a neighbour of the <hi>Devizes,</hi> and an acquaintance of his after, that came by him to <hi>Briſtoll</hi> Fair, and ſeveral ſpeakings to his Book-ſeller to write to him to that end, who ſtill told me he ſtaid the Preſs for my ſecond Impreſſion, having been ready for it ſome months) had no ſignification, if my Letter had not in time reach'd him, to prevent that diſturbance, or at leaſt to have obtained ſome Civil return from him.</p>
            <p>Well, the Book comes forth, and how ſtufft with prejudice, perſonal Reflections, egregious Miſtakes, bitter Invectives not only againſt my ſelf, and whole Party, but the Principle it ſelf, you are beſt able to judge; which I endeavoured ſome time after, notwithſtanding all thoſe high provocations given, modeſtly to detect in a ſober Reply.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:5"/>
            <p>Though by the way this piece of Civility and Ingenuity muſt not be forgotten, that the week before my Reply was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, they thought meet to put Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> Title into the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zette,</hi> to proclaim me a Forger all the Nation over, knowing that though I might follow him in the Preſs, yet there I was not capable to attend him for my Vindication.</p>
            <p>Some months after mine came forth, I heard Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> was come to Town with a Rejoynder: whereupon I ſent ſome Friends to him to prevail for a Conference with him, which could not be obtained. Then I wrote to ſome of his Friends to acquaint him, that if he would meet with two or three Chriſtian Friends of a ſide, and communicate to me his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, I ſhould aſſure him, that if I had done him or the Truth any injury, I would make the moſt publick ſatisfaction that they ſhould judge requiſite; which could not prevail with him. Afterwards I hearing that he had been with my Book-ſeller, to read ſome writing of mine reſpecting the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, which was ſhewed him, and ſuppoſing that might be ſome obligation to him to be reciprocal, did ſend my Book-ſeller to his to obtain the like freedom, to peruſe his Papers in his Book-ſellers hand, but could obtain no permiſſion thereto.</p>
            <p>And yet after the rejection of all theſe modeſt endeavours of my part, which beſpoke me far from being obſtinate or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious in any thing that I had writ, he has the Confidence with this clap of Thunder he has come forth with, to tell the world in his Ep. to his <hi>Vindiciae, That he muſt acquaint me that I having treated him with ſo much rudeneſs in what is paſt, that he had little heart to have any more to do with me, unleſs he ſee better cauſe, and gives me ſecurity of his Silence for the future, to any of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, there being no gaping againſt an oven, and ſilence is accounted the beſt anſwer to ſuch as ſuper-add contumacy to their miſtakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where has that Contumacy appeared in me? It is true he deals with me in his appeal as a contumacious perſon, but
<pb facs="tcp:199364:6"/> how ſuch proceedings are to be reconciled to Reaſon, Rule, or Religion, I muſt confeſs my ſelf at a great loſs.</p>
            <p>Had he dealt with me herein as the Quakers dealt with Mr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> which he makes his pattern, he had been much more excuſable, who (I preſume he'l find) admitted of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conference, and had Letters exchanged betwixt them; and till they ſuppoſed Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> was contumacious, and tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, did not proceed in that their Appeal.</p>
            <p>I do not know that it is the practice in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> for a Plaintiff to procure publication for Tryal before he gives his Declaration, has his Anſwer, Reply, Rejoynder, &amp;c. and ſurely Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> ſhould have had ſo much patience to have attended what I had ſaid to his <hi>Vindiciae,</hi> before he had thundred out his Appeal: It may be my Anſwer to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, might have prevented the latter. Will nothing ſatisfie him but my utmoſt ſhame and reproach? Yet would he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world, <hi>That he loves me as a Brother though erring, and had much rather convince then ſhame me, adviſing me to leave toſſing the Ball of contention,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But is this dealing with me like a Brother he deſigns to convince and reduce from errour? Is this to inſtruct with meekneſs? to uſe any Goſpel-way to reform and inform, he knows the Soveraign Rule <hi>Mat. 18.</hi> is not publickly to tell the Church, till all other private ways are ineffectual.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs theſe are ways and ſtrains that I have not been acquainted withall, either amongſt men or Chriſtians, which only ſerve as to my own particular to lead me to Chriſts rule, which I deſire more to attend in the caſe, To pray for him that thus deſpitefully uſes and perſecutes me, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce that I am counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame, and to have all manner of evil ſpoken againſt me falſly for his Names ſake.</p>
            <p>Withall ſatisfying my ſelf that Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> takes the ready way by theſe methods to promote the cauſe he oppoſes, for few that ever I heard of, that manage a good cauſe, are left to ſuch foul miſcarriages.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199364:6"/>
            <head>The Antiquity of Believers, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of Infants Baptiſm.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>GHAP. I.</hi> Wherein the Antiquity of Believers, and Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Infants Baptiſm is further confirmed; and that the Baptiſm after Faith was the only Baptiſm that was owned in the firſt <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies,</hi> to be Chriſts Ordinance and the Churches Practiſe, in full Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his <hi>Vindiciae.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE main queſtion diſcuſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> and me, has been, whether the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> (ſo called) or the <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> have moſt to plead from <hi>Antiquity</hi> for their Way; <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe that only <hi>Baptize</hi> Men and Women after <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of Faith and Repentance, or thoſe that Baptize <hi>Infants</hi> that are capable of neither.</p>
               <p>The former of which I firſt aſſerted in my <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and ſince defended, in my Reply to Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and others, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> notwithſtanding the great <hi>Cry</hi> to the contrary, have the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of their <hi>ſide</hi> for the firſt <hi>Centuries.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199364:7"/>
               <p>And which notwithſtanding all the noiſe and clamour after the full diſcuſſion of that point on both hands, is now clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted (if not by their own grants confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to us. The which you may receive in the following brief <hi>Account.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CENT.</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1. Cent.</hi> gives Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</note>FIrſt it is moſt <hi>manifeſt</hi> as is confeſt on all hands, that the Scripture Story for the firſt <hi>Century</hi> gives us an account of no other Baptiſm, but that after Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>viz.</hi> Produceth Inſtances, or gives us Examples only for adult Believers, and not Infants Baptiſm; As we have obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> themſelves thoſe <hi>Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobaptiſts</hi> have ſo fully own'd acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That they find Examples in the</hi> 2, 8, 10, 16, 19. <hi>of the Acts for the Baptizing of adult Believers, hut of Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>izing of Infants they read of no Example</hi> De Infantibus Baptizatis Exempla quidem non leguntur: To which Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> ſubſcribes, acknowledging, <hi>That there are no particular Examples for Infants Baptiſm upon Record,</hi> p. 3. 53. vind. Mr. <hi>Whitſton</hi> confeſſing <hi>the ſame as generally</hi> own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them.</p>
                  <p>As for the Allegation, That the <hi>Apoſtles Writings</hi> do not expreſly exclude In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ants, as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199364:7"/> Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whitſton</hi> from the <hi>Magd.</hi> affirm is ſo weak and frivolous, that needs no Reply, which would eſtabliſh Baptizing of Bells, Chryſm, and what not of the Popiſh Inventions.</p>
                  <p>And that if not aſſerted in Scripture, is yet found in the Writings of <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> to have been the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> practiſe, is as ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly inſignificant; for as it has, and will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear to you they have writ no <hi>ſuch thing;</hi> nor ſecondly if they <hi>had,</hi> would what they <hi>writ</hi> in the third Age, upon their ſingle <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> prove ſuch a matter of <hi>fact</hi> in the firſt Age, when as 'tis confeſt the Scripture is wholly ſilent <hi>therein.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore I hope it cannot be <hi>denyed,</hi> that for what appears in <hi>Scripture Story<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themſelves being <hi>Judges,</hi> that <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> for the firſt <hi>Century</hi> is wholly on our ſide; ſo that no mention need be made of the Epiſtles of <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Ignatius</hi> in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CENT.</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>SEcondly, as to the Second <hi>Century</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2. Cent.</hi> gives Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</note> we find upon the fulleſt diſcuſſion, it <hi>produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth</hi> as few Examples for Infants Baptiſm, as the firſt, and that only thoſe are mentioned to have been <hi>Baptized in this Age,</hi> that firſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199364:8"/> made <hi>a profeſsion of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> as appears by that moſt remarkable account given us out of <hi>Juſtin Martyrs Apology,</hi> the moſt Authentick piece of <hi>Antiquity</hi> of this Age (not to mention what is ſaid from <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius,</hi> and <hi>Clem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt. Alexandrinus</hi> Treat. p. 49, 50. which is not gainſaid by our <hi>Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt,</hi> only Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> would inſinuate, that the <hi>Magd.</hi> did ſuppoſe, <hi>That the Order</hi> Juſtin Martyr <hi>lays down, reſpected the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Aliens to Baptiſm,</hi> which would not hurt us, becauſe all are Aliens till Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, no mention being made of any that were otherwiſe received. But <hi>Juſtins</hi> own words are full for ſatisfaction in the point, as <hi>Treat p.</hi> 49. viz. <hi>I will declare unto you how we offer up our ſelves to God after we are renewed through Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Which reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Order and Method obſerved by the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Believers</hi> in the Church at that day, and how all of them had their <hi>admiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> therein.</p>
                  <p>So that for the firſt 200 <hi>Years</hi> we carry it, having Examples as is confeſt for <hi>the one,</hi> but none to be produced for <hi>the other:</hi> Whereby I ſhould be ſufficiently <hi>juſtified,</hi> (ſhould we proceed no farther) in that <hi>aſser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> ſo complains of, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>vind.</hi> By affirming, That Antiquity it ſelf is <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for Believers, and not for Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199364:8"/> For if it be manifeſt, that there be 200 Years for <hi>the one</hi> before <hi>the other,</hi> well may I ſay, That there is <hi>Antiqity</hi> for <hi>the one,</hi> and not for <hi>the other;</hi> for if <hi>Antiquity</hi> be writ upon <hi>Believers Baptiſm, Novelty</hi> then muſt needs be writ upon <hi>Infants Baptiſm.</hi> Nor but that I grant ſome that were called the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> of the 5th. Age, as <hi>Auſtin, Chryſoſtom,</hi> and others affirmed it; from whence Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> again and again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids me, and Mr. <hi>Whitſton</hi> alſo, That I do contradict <hi>my ſelf,</hi> in ſaying <hi>Antiquity</hi> was altogether for <hi>the one,</hi> and not for <hi>the other,</hi> they not conſidering, or <hi>willingly omit</hi> that I mean <hi>Primitive Antiquity;</hi> the Elder Brother was to carry away, as the <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> and <hi>preheminency,</hi> ſo the Inheritance from the Younger, much more the true <hi>born,</hi> from the baſe <hi>born Child.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CENT.</hi> III.</head>
                  <p>IN the 3d. <hi>Century</hi> we have as few <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> to be produced for <hi>Infants Baptiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">No Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for any but Adult Baptiſm in the <hi>3. Cen.</hi>
                     </note> as in the two <hi>former;</hi> but that they Baptized in this <hi>Age</hi> after the Profeſſion of Faith, we have an ample account from <hi>Tertullian, Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and ſeveral others, as <hi>Treat. p.</hi> 51, &amp;c. And which our Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts are ſo far from oppoſing, that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199364:9"/> abundantly confirm, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> p. 1. cap. 8. ſect. 5. telling us, <hi>That</hi> Tertullian, Origen, Cyprian, <hi>who lived</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the</hi> 2d. <hi>and</hi> 3d. Centuries, <hi>do all of them affirm, That in the Primitive times none were Baptized without an expreſs Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting, wherein they renounced the World; Fleſh, and Devil, and engaged themſelves to Chriſt, and promiſed to obey him.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> alſo, 2. <hi>part. p.</hi> 6. of Infants Baptiſm, acknowledgeth, <hi>That the</hi> Magdeburgs <hi>do tell us, Thaet</hi> Tertullian <hi>in this age oppoſed himſelf to ſome that aſſerted Infants Baptiſm, affirming, That the Adult were only proper Subjects.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that it is manifeſt by what appears up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record from any Authentick Story, that <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> carries the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the Third <hi>Century</hi> alſo; there being not as yet one Infant upon Record that was actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Baptized, as any Ordinance of Chriſt, nor any thing appearing from good Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by any Scripture Argument, that they ought ſo to be: What is pretended from <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> you have fully replyed to afterwards, and the utter inſignificancy of any thing that is urged from them to this end, whilſt you have full mouthed Evidence, and undeniable Authority for the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="century">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199364:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CENT.</hi> IV.</head>
                  <p>AS to the 4th. <hi>Century</hi> it doth not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear when and where any Infant was Baptized, as an Ordinance of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Adult Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm the general practiſe of the <hi>4th.</hi> Age.</note> it is ſaid indeed that ſome <hi>Sick Children</hi> were Baptized for their Health in this Age, and that ſome <hi>Dying Children might be Baptized</hi> to ſave them, as ſome other <hi>Dying Perſons</hi> were; and that ſome <hi>Doctors</hi> in this Age enclined from <hi>Circumciſion</hi> to bring it into the <hi>Church;</hi> but as yet none did pretend it to be neceſſary, none to have been a Precept of the Goſpel, as Dr. <hi>Taylor Treat. p.</hi> 105. Whereas the Baptizing of Believers after the Profeſſion of Faith, was the general practiſe of the Age, and which appears from the Three Subſtantial Inſtances given by me in my Treatiſe, eſpecially in the Reply, <hi>viz.</hi> From 1. the <hi>Sayings of Fathers.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1ſt.</hi> From the Sayings of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> 2. <hi>Decrees of Councils.</hi> 3. <hi>Children of Believers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized till aged,</hi> p. 4, &amp;c. 1. From the Sayings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and greateſt Men of this <hi>Century,</hi> both in<note n="(a)" place="margin">Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius <hi>and</hi> Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius.</note> 
                     <hi>Affrica,</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Baſil, Nazianzen, Eph. Syrus, Epiphanius.</note> 
                     <hi>Aſiae,</hi> and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Hillarii, Ambroſe, Jerom, Marius Victorinus.</note> 
                     <hi>Europe,</hi> aſſerting the neceſſity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith before <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> both from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199364:10"/> Chriſts <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> Apoſtles <hi>Practiſe,</hi> and ends of the <hi>Ordinance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> little oppoſeth, only ſaith, <hi>That ſome of theſe Doctors were corrupt in other things,</hi> and ſo they were all, <hi>That ſome of them</hi> 3 <hi>or</hi> 4 <hi>aſſerted Infants Baptiſm;</hi> which I deny not, to ſave Dying Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; ſaith one of them, <hi>viz.</hi> Arnobius <hi>was ſpurious from</hi> Perkins; what then? the reſt are <hi>genuine;</hi> and that <hi>Arnobius</hi> on the Pſalms was ever Doubted is more <hi>than I heard</hi> before; but if he was, it ſignifies <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> he alſo <hi>Doubts</hi> Baſils <hi>Proof,</hi> urged by me <hi>contra Eunomium,</hi> which he calls for, and which he'l find <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>p,</hi> 24. viz. <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is the Seal of Faith, but Faith is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of the Diety; for Firſt he ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and after to be Sealed with Baptiſm.</hi> Doubts <hi>whether</hi> Athanaſius <hi>is rightly rendred,</hi> for which I give you my Authority<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>That what is urged for the neceſsity of Faith to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede Baptiſm, reſpected the Adult,</hi> very true: And <hi>that ſome were for the Baptiſm of Infants, who were not capable to make Confeſsion;</hi> very true alſo; <hi>Si aliquid periculi immineat,</hi> If any danger happned otherwiſe, the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity thereof from any precept of Chriſt was not yet enjoyed.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199364:10"/>2. As to the 3 Councils,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Decrees of Council.</note> (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginian, Laodicean,</hi> and <hi>Neoceſarian</hi>) ſo poſitively decreeing, That <hi>Teaching, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Faith,</hi> and <hi>free choice,</hi> ought to precede <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>That theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees reſpected the Adult;</hi> very true; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not Infants. <hi>That the Council of</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage <hi>and</hi> Laodicea <hi>Decreed alſo for Exorciſm, and giving the Euchariſt to dying Perſons, and Penance</hi> &amp;c. What then, if they were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in other things, were they not right here? Moſt of the <hi>Fathers</hi> were for theſe <hi>Corruptions</hi> alſo. And that as to the <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſarean Council</hi> he ſaith, <hi>He had as much cauſe to queſtion, whether there was any ſuch Council, as I had to queſtion</hi> Cyprians Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. But herein he will find himſelf much miſtaken, whilſt the <hi>Magdeburghs,</hi> Cent. 4 c. 9. p, 615. give the <hi>Biſhops Names</hi> who ſat in this <hi>Council,</hi> the <hi>time</hi> when it ſat, <hi>viz.</hi> Immediately after that of <hi>Anoyranus,</hi> which <hi>Helvicus</hi> makes to be about the 10 or 12 of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> Together with the 14 Canons of which this is one expreſt at large, and which Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> gives us in <hi>the Original Greek, Determining as he ſaith, that none ought to be Baptized without giving an account of their Faith, and deſiring the ſame,</hi> Whilſt Mr. <hi>VVills</hi> can neither produce from any <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Authentick Authority, when,</hi> or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199364:11"/> 
                     <hi>where</hi> Cyprians <hi>Council</hi> ſat, or what they <hi>decreed</hi> or <hi>determined</hi> in that <hi>Council,</hi> but what is pretended from that <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> which for its corruption is ſo much queſtioned, whereof more hereafter.</p>
                  <p>The 3d. Inſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> from 10 of the moſt eminent Men of the Age, who were not Baptized till aged,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>3.</hi> From <hi>10</hi> of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent men, not Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed till aged.</note> though the Children of Chriſtian Parents, <hi>viz. Bazel, Gregory, Nazianzen, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtom, Jerom, Auſtin, Nectarius, Conſtantine, Valentinian,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius.</hi> Concerning whom, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting: Two of them, <hi>viz. Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Auſtin.</hi> he tells me <hi>he will not contend with me, but for them he doubts whether their Parents were Chriſtian,</hi> yet denies not but that <hi>Dr.</hi> Taylor <hi>and Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>may have been of my mind,</hi> whilſt ſome others wirh himſelf have denyed it, which will be of great force with any conſidering perſons; for if they had judged it an Ordinance of Chriſt, ſo many of the Chief of the Age would not ſo have neglected it.</p>
                  <p>In the next place Mr. <hi>VVills</hi> quarrels with ſome of my modern <hi>Authors,</hi> who ſpeak the ſame thing, <hi>viz. That in theſe fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt times none were Baptized without prefeſsion of Faith,</hi> viz. <hi>Strabo Rhevanus Rupertus Boemus</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> eſpecially queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Rhenanus</hi> and <hi>Rupertus</hi> for Forgery; the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199364:11"/> firſt I grant you is not proper to prove only ſuch were Baptized, that tearm only being not in it as in all the reſt, but is no Forgery. As for <hi>Rupertus,</hi> 'tis no <hi>Forgery;</hi> the Treat. ſaith, They adminiſtred <hi>Baptiſm</hi> only to the <hi>Children of the Church</hi> at <hi>Eaſter;</hi> the Reply ſaith only the <hi>Cathechumens,</hi> which as I take it is one and the ſame, as it reſpects the <hi>Children of the Church,</hi> who it ſeems <hi>were not Baptized till aged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But concerning Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and my abuſing him, reſpecting his witneſs, that <hi>Adult Baptiſm was the only neceſſary Baptiſm in theſe times,</hi> take his own words ſo lately given us in his More Proofs, <hi>p.</hi> 279. viz. <hi>Yet again I will confeſs, That the words of</hi> Tertullian <hi>and</hi> Nazianzen <hi>ſhew,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr. B's</hi> full grant againſt the Antiquity of Infants Baptiſm.</note> 
                     <hi>that it was long before all were agreed of the very time, or of the neceſſity of Baptizing Infants before any uſe of reaſon, in caſe they were like to live to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, for I am perſwaded, that the Apoſtles and firſt Miniſters were ſo taken up with the Converting of Infidels, Jews and Gentiles, that the caſe of Infant Baptiſm was ſo poſt-poned, and taken up as an Appendix to the Baptiſm of the Adult, as that it was thought leſs needful to give it a particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs mention in the Records and Hiſtory of the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> own Pen has given himſelf <hi>the lye,</hi> and juſt rebuke for all his vain <hi>jangle</hi> about the point of <hi>Antiquity</hi> for <hi>Infants Baptiſm,</hi> which now he is thus forc'd to confeſs the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is no expreſs mention in the <hi>Records and Hiſtory of the Church for,</hi> and ſo alſo at once ſpoil'd all Mr. <hi>Wills daubery,</hi> and <hi>ſilly Wranglings</hi> about this Point.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199364:12"/>
                  <p>Therefore I hope it will not now be denyed us that the Anabaptiſts have the Antiquity on their ſide, not only for the firſt 200, but for the firſt 400 years, there being <hi>nothing in the Records of Church Hiſtory,</hi> as is manifeſt, and confeſt to us alſo, to prove any <hi>Infant was Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,</hi> as a <hi>Church Ordinance,</hi> or that they ought in point of <hi>neceſſity</hi> ſo to be; and therefore there is no cauſe to queſtion the truth of Dr. <hi>Taylors,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Barlows</hi> poſitive aſſertions in concurrence herewith, and in confirmation hereof remark'd to us: And it is worthy of conſideration, that Dr. <hi>Barlow,</hi> in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getical <hi>Lr.</hi> printed by Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> doth not gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the Reaſon and Truth of what he formerly affirmed, but the indiſcretion of writing, and unfaithfulneſs of printing the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CENT.</hi> V.</head>
                  <p>THe Fifth <hi>Century,</hi> as we have at large proved <hi>Treat. p.</hi> 105, &amp;c. brings in the neceſſity of <hi>Infants Baptiſm</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>5. Cent.</hi> Brings in and impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Infants Baptiſm.</note> to <hi>regenerate, take away</hi> ſin, and to <hi>ſave the Soul</hi> of the Infant, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there was no <hi>Salvation</hi> to be had for them, grounded upon <hi>John</hi> 3.5. as determined in the <hi>Milevitan,</hi> and afterwards in the <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginian Councils,</hi> by Pope <hi>Innocentius,</hi> afterwards confirmed by Pope <hi>Zozimus,</hi> and afterwards by Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> &amp;c. Never determined ſaith Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> till the Canon made in the <hi>Milevitan Council,</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Strabo, Luther, Grotius,</hi> Treat. p. 107. which afterwards by degrees came <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally</hi> to be received both <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt.</hi> Yet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199364:12"/> withall this is moſt remarkable in the enjoyning thereof, that the <hi>appointing of Goſſips to confeſs Faith, and profeſs repentance in the name and ſtead of the Child before Baptiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Goſſips confirm the neceſſity of profeſſion before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</note> and the practiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ever ſince to this our day, was a great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation that the truth of the principle was owned, that Chriſt enjoyned in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, requiring Faith ſhould precede, and a Witneſs of the ancient practiſe of perſonal profeſſion in the former Centuries. This In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention being found out purpoſely to anſwer the Commiſſion: And therefore ſaith <hi>Lud. Vives l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>That none were Baptized of old but thoſe of age, who did not only underſtand what the Water meant, but deſired the ſame; the perfect Image whereof</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we have yet in our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm; for it is ask'd of the Infant, wilt thou be Baptized? for whom the Sureties anſwer, I will.</hi> And ſo ſaith <hi>Strabo</hi> Treat. <hi>p.</hi> 63. and <hi>Boemus</hi> p. 73. And upon this account both <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Chryſoſtom,</hi> and the Doctors and Learned Men produced by me downwards through the Papacy to our day, ſpoke ſo much (from Chriſts Commiſſion, and primitive Saints practiſe) for the neceſſity of Faith and Repentance before Baptiſm, only by their Sureties. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did I ſo loudly call upon Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> to prove Goſſips to be an appointment of Chriſt, or elſe to allow me all thoſe Paedobaptiſts for proper Witneſſes for Believers, and againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſm, and to free me from the many Forgeries he loaded me with for the ſame. But inſtead of doing himſelf and me right therein, he only returns thus to me, <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>vind. Mr.</hi> Danvers <hi>brings Teſtimony for Adult Baptiſm foom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199364:13"/> Paedobaptiſts, and It ſeems aſtrange deſign to all that I have ſpoken with about the ſame, that he ſhould offer to bring,</hi> Chryſoſtom, Auſtin, <hi>&amp;c. againſt Infant Baptiſm, ſo making the Fathers to contradict themſelves, and for which I rebuke him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> declines anſwering the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial point about Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſips.</note>
                     <hi>But he takes much pains to vindicate himſelf, in which undertaking I find him ſo full of Meanders, and tedious Circumlocutions, that I judge it not worth the while to follow him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By which his declining to anſwer ſo material a thing, we muſt take it for granted he cannot, and therefore muſt ſtill apply all <hi>thoſe Authorities</hi> from <hi>Paedobaptiſts,</hi> even from <hi>Auſtin</hi> to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in full Confirmation of the practiſe of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> in their Baptizing only after profeſſion, and in point blank <hi>contradiction</hi> to their own practiſe of Baptizing Infants, who are ſo uncapable either to anſwer the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, primitive Saints practiſe, or the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ends of that great Ordinance, and ſo our whole Witneſs ſtands good, as not anſwered or owned by themſelves. As to what he ſaith reſpecting thoſe ſeveral falſhoods returned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; and the abſurdities made out againſt him about Tradition, from <hi>p.</hi> 51. to 83. I only deſire the Reader to examine the ſhortneſs and inſufficiency of his Anſwers by the Reply, from <hi>p.</hi> 29 to 79. it being not worth while to trouble them with his ſilly wranglings animated by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, as Mr. <hi>B.</hi> phraſes it. And it muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred to him that as to thoſe Stories about <hi>John a Leyden,</hi> for which he reflected ſo much obliquy upon the way of Anabaptiſtry; which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned upon him, and his great error and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Story evinced with his malicious ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199364:13"/> and falſe reports he therein publiſhed, not only againſt the <hi>Holland,</hi> but <hi>Engliſh</hi> Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts diſcovered to him: Concerning all which he makes no return, and whoſe ſilence therein muſt be taken for his guilt, and bound upon him at leaſt till he vindicate himſelf, or own his folly and injuſtice. As alſo in his ſaying nothing to the Arguments for dipping, againſt ſprinkling or pouring, (about which he has made ſuch a flouriſh heretofore) is becauſe if he be not wholly convinced, yet that he is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially ſilenced, and can ſay nothing thereto.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, as to what he has ſaid againſt our Poſitive Witneſſes againſt Infants Baptiſm, we muſt refer him to what is ſaid to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> after whoſe Copy he writes, and he having ſo fully granted us <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted as before, that the <hi>Beringarians, Wickliffians,</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes</hi> were againſt Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Infants for Salvation, <hi>Manichees</hi> were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt it, who were no other than <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes.</hi> The whole of the Book ſtands yet firm and untouch'd, and moſt of it confirmed and eſtabliſhed by their own Pens.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199364:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Some Objections about <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and others, anſwered.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> MR. <hi>Wills</hi> tells me, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>That I ſilently paſs by what the</hi> Magdeburgs <hi>do expreſly ſay was in uſe in the</hi> 3d. <hi>age.</hi> viz. <hi>That adult Perſons of both Sexes, and alſo Infants were Baptized,</hi> Cent. 3. c. 6. p. 124.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> That I have nor paſt it by will eaſily be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, when it is conſidered what I have ſaid to the Authorities they give for the ſame in the ſaid place, <hi>Cent.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 124. viz. <hi>Origens Hom. on Leviticus, and Cyprians Epiſt. to Fidus,</hi> neither of which proving, as I ſuppoſe, ſufficient Authority upon the tryal to make good the ſame. The Words of the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> are theſe, <hi>Baptizabantur autem in utro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſexu adulti ſimul &amp; infantes, That adult Perſons of both Sexes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were Baptized. Nam de Infantibus Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zandis Origines Homil</hi> 8. <hi>in leviticum, Eccleſiam ait traditionem accepiſſe ab Apoſtolis: Et Cyprianus</hi> l. 3. Ep. 8. <hi>For concerning the Baptizing of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Origens 8 <hi>Homily on</hi> Leviticus <hi>ſaith, That the Church received it as a Tradition from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and</hi> Cyprians 8 <hi>Epiſtle in his</hi> 3d. <hi>Book to</hi> Fidus. <hi>Contra quod tamen etiam</hi> Tertullian <hi>cenſuit in lib. de Bapt. Notwithſtanding</hi> Tertullian <hi>thought otherwiſe in his Book of Baptiſm,</hi> (mind that.)</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199364:14"/>
               <p>The Arguments brought from <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> have been examined at large in my <hi>Treat. p.</hi> 124. to 151. and further in the <hi>Reply p.</hi> 84. to 97. where I prove that of <hi>Origens</hi> to be <hi>Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Origens <hi>Teſtimony examined.</hi>
                  </note> and not only that upon <hi>Levit.</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> which Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> cannot now deny, [whereby the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> proof is out of doors] but what he ſaith alſo upon <hi>Luke,</hi> with my grounds urged for the ſame from <hi>Voſſius, Scultetus, Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi> (1) Becauſe the Original is not extant. (2) Becauſe what is therein pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended from <hi>Origen, viz.</hi> That Children muſt be Baptized to take away Orignal ſin, (ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his own judgment) he being the head of the <hi>Arrians.</hi> Therefore how fair this is for Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> to boaſt of this Antiquity, and yet decline Anſwering to their Arguments, I leave all Men to judge. Who is pleaſed without any one word of Anſwer to that which is ſo poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſaid to enervate what is pretended for <hi>Luke,</hi> yet in a ſcurilous and pedantick way to ſay <hi>p.</hi> 93 <hi>Vind. We ſee by what is ſaid, That we have Infants Baptiſm owned, as from the Apoſtles, by</hi> Origen <hi>on</hi> Luke, <hi>what ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r becomes on the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, <hi>and tranſlated by</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. So that the Fabreck ſtands yet uprig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, never like to be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd by Mr.</hi> Danvers, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat ever great Exploits he hath done heretofore in the days of his Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning which proof from <hi>Origen,</hi> you have Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> in his liberty of Prophecy, <hi>p.</hi> 237. Thus,<note place="margin">D. <hi>Taylors</hi> full wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt <hi>Origens</hi> Teſtimony.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. None of the reformed Churches can pretend this Argument for this opinion: Becauſe they who reject Tradition, when it is againſt them, muſt not pretend it in the leaſt for them; but if
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199364:15"/> the Topick be allowed to be good, yet how will it be verified? For ſo far as can yet appear, it relies wholly upon the Teſtimony of</hi> Origen, <hi>for from him</hi> Auſtin <hi>had it, a Perſon whom all other Ages have condemned of Errors, and whoſe works have been judged ſo ſpurious.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that it was the opinion of the Primitive Church, That Infants ought not to be Baptized, is cleer, faith he, in the Canon of the Council of</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſaria, <hi>determining, that none ought to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized without giving an account of their Faith, and deſiring the ſame.</hi> And agreeable hereto witneſſing the rhe Doctor, ſpoke fully his own ſence herein, take that parallel paſſage writ in one of his laſt pieces, in his <hi>Diſſwaſive againſt Popery,</hi> writ 1667. <hi>viz. That there is a Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Baptize Ynfants relies but upon Two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses,</hi> Origen <hi>and</hi> Auſtin, <hi>and the latter having received it from the former, it relies wholly upon a ſingle Teſtimony, which is but a pittiful Argument to prove a Tradition Apoſtolical, he is the firſt that ſpoke it, but</hi> Tertullian <hi>that was before him ſeems ſpeak againſt, which he would not have done, if it bad been a Tradition Apoſtolical, and that it was not ſo, it is but too certain, if there be any Truth in the woriss of</hi> Lud. Vives, <hi>ſaying, that anciently none were Baptized but Perſons of riper Ages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theo exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</note>Then as to <hi>Cyprians Ep.</hi> to <hi>Fidus,</hi> (which is ſo much lean'd upon, the other proving but a broken Reed) ſuppoſing there was ſuch a Council; (which yet no Author can tell us when, and where held, and what therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined) and that this Epiſtle was genuine, (againſt which I have much to ſay, <hi>Stephens, Daylle, Eraſmus,</hi> and others proving how much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199364:15"/> his Works as well as <hi>Origens</hi> have been abuſed, and things fathered upon him that were never his) yet the erronious grounds upon which Infants Bahtiſm is aſſerted therein, takes away the <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the ſaid Council, determining as one well ſaith <hi>Childrens Baptiſm, by ſuch Childiſh Reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the matter of Fact ſay they is clear, which witneſſed, that the Church had then ſuch a <hi>practiſe,</hi> and which all our three Adverſaries much inſiſt upon,</p>
               <p>As to matter of Fact in Antiquity, (if this ſhould be granted, of which I ſee not much cauſe, for at beſt it was but advice, and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on erroneous grounds too, no Preſident as yet apparing in the Caſe) it would ſignifie little to create a practiſe from it. For that Children were Baptized for <hi>health,</hi> and Church Walls were alſo ſolemnly Baptized for dedication, and after that Bells <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot be denyed, ſhall we therefore be warranted to do the like from thoſe Preſidents? But in as much as here was no Example, or matter of Fact, nor any advice but upon corrupt and erroneous <hi>grounds,</hi> this can ſignifie nothing; the grounds of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice being rejected by the <hi>Paedobaptiſts,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the advice it ſelf as to matter of Fact is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected be them alſo; all that can be gathered from it, if true, is only that ſuch a Cuſtom was creeping in. We know giving the <hi>Sacrament</hi> to Infants is ſuppoſed to be very <hi>ancient,</hi> and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued very long in uſe 600 years, ſaith <hi>Maldonat</hi> on <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. and that amongſt the <hi>Greeks</hi> as well as <hi>Latins,</hi> aſſiſted by <hi>Auſtin, Innocent,</hi> &amp; others, (if not by <hi>Cyprian</hi> alſo) &amp; that it was <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> or foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199364:16"/> upon the Scriptures, but is not that rejected?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But holy</hi> Cyprian, <hi>ſaith Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>tells us, as</hi> p. 276. <hi>More Proofs,</hi> was <hi>an eminent worthy, a great Father and Pillar of the Church, and ought not to be ſlighted.</hi> Yet by his leave Father <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> was not Father <hi>Paul,</hi> nor any <hi>Apoſtle to us,</hi> nor doth he give us any warranty from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and Chrlſts Precept to ground ſuch a practiſe upon, but the <hi>contrary,</hi> and that which <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> now a days reject, as very erroneous. And if he tells us, we ſhould do any thing as Apoſtolical without a word, we muſt give as little credit to him, as when he tells us, <hi>Chryſm</hi> is ſo, (which the <hi>Magd.</hi> tell us he doth, <hi>Cent.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 82. out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> l. 1. Ep. 12. though Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> denies the ſame) or as when he tells us of <hi>the neceſſity of Exorciſms, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of</hi> Peters <hi>Chair, Alms to take away ſin, that the Adminiſtrator gives the Spirit in the act of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> of <hi>Rebaptization,</hi> by undoubted Councils confirmed, <hi>Perfuſion of the Clinici, Diluting of Wine,</hi> or <hi>mingling Water with it</hi> in the Sacrament <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have been the larger upon theſe Two, <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> becauſe my Three Antagoniſts, and others, do lay ſo much ſtreſs upon them, to prove their Antiquity from, but how little they ſignifie you now ſee.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ended the point of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and which we ſhall conclude with an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the Learned<note place="margin">An Appeal to the Learned.</note> of all perſwaſions, <hi>Whether there is not good cauſe to write Antiquity upon Believers, and Novelty upon Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm;</hi> Nothing more appearing for it for the Four firſt <hi>Centuries,</hi> than has yet been brought forth by our oppoſites, And ſo much for the <hi>Antiquity of Believers Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199364:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Gives anſwer to Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his Appeal in all the parts of it.</head>
               <p>THe better to help the <hi>Appellants (viz.</hi> the <hi>Baptiſts</hi>) to give a righteous judgment in the matters brought to their Barr, by Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> in his Appeal: And for the ſatisfaction of all men, I do hereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyn iſſue with him in the candid examination thereof.</p>
               <div n="1" type="complaint">
                  <head>Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his Appeal to the Baptiſts, as you find, conſiſts of <hi>8</hi> Complaints, the which I diſtinctly anſwer as followeth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. His firſt Complaint againſt me is,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>For leaving out part of what my Authors ſay, to make the Sentence more for my purpoſe; and for which he gives ſix Inſtances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In Reply whereto, I firſt ſay in general,<note place="margin">Anſwered. <hi>1.</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</note> That in the quoting of Authors we are obliged to give only what they ſpeak to the thing in hand, without unneceſſary repetitions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> in his own caſe, when I blamed him <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>Reply,</hi> for leaving out part of that remarkable Sentence out of <hi>Nazianzen, viz.</hi> where he brings him to affirm, <hi>That a Child may be Baptized,</hi> leaving out the next words, <hi>ſi aliquid periculi imminoat, if any thing of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger happened.</hi> And in Excuſe thereof is pleaſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199364:17"/> to make the following return <hi>Vind. p.</hi> 7. viz. <hi>That I do exclaim againſt him for Curtailing that Father. but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Judicious Reader may underſtand, that he quarrels at me without cauſe; for my buſineſs was to prove, That Infant Baptiſm was owned in that Century as to matter of Fact, and not to diſcover the ground of it, or to enquire in what Caſes it was done; and therefore he might have ſpared his frivolous Charge about that matter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Rule of his own, however it may ſerve to relieve him for leaving out that paſſage, (which I doubt, and is not now my b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſineſs to diſpute) to be ſure it will juſtine me in all the 6 Particulars charged upon me under this head. Yet this by the way, as to the reaſon of his omitting that paſſage; <hi>becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the former words the matter of fact is to be made good, (viz.</hi> That Infant Baptiſm was own'd in this Century) <hi>is manifeſt.</hi> But he knows the Queſtion is not, Whether an Infant might be Baptized; for at another time he can tell us, <hi>That e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ery Baptiſm is not the Baptiſm intended, but only that which is done in Chriſts way in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Rule.</hi> So that if a Child was Dipt, which it might be accidentally by chance, or occaſionally upon ſome emergency, or Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinally to cure Diſeaſes, (as ſome were in this Age) or ſuperſtitiouſly to ſave its dying Soul, which was onely the fancy intended in this place, (and therefore ſhould not have been omitted, for ſpoiling the ſcope) it would ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing, being no Baptiſm of Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, the matter of fact being only to be made out, when the neceſſity of ſuch a practiſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199364:17"/> in obedience to Chriſts Command in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Goſpel Ordinance is proved. And which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> grants us, was not as yet to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by any Church Record; and never till the <hi>Milevitan Council,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the next place, for your better ſatisfaction,<note place="margin">2ly <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</hi>
                     </note> I ſhall ſpeak to each Particular: And,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, as to the quotation out of <hi>Daille</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>About</hi> Dailles.</note> 
                     <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>p</hi> 149. mentioned <hi>Treat. p.</hi> 62. My buſineſs was therein to diſcover, That the Ancients de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred Infants Baptiſm, therefore I gave the ſeveral Inſtances from him of thoſe who had their Baptiſm de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erred till aged, <hi>viz. Ambroſe, Nazianzen, Bazil,</hi> &amp;c. who appear undeniably to have been the Children of Chriſtian Parents, and <hi>that it was,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>the opinion of ſome of the Fathers, That it is fit Infants Baptiſm ſhould be deferred: And how comes it to paſs, that there is not the leaſt tracing or footing of this Cuſtom in the Church of</hi> Rome. <hi>Nay, whence is it beſides, that they will not ſo much as endure the very men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and would abhor the Man that ſhould go about to practiſe it,</hi> (the Truth whereof we find alſo, and feel) <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>Wills, Daille</hi> mentions the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Baptiſm of other people alſo, and why did I leave that out? For the Reaſon Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> gives, becauſe it was not ſo much <hi>ad rem.</hi> Though if I had, it would have done him no ſervice, it <hi>Daille</hi> underſtood himſelf, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers us to what he had before ſpoken about it, which we find in <hi>p.</hi> 72. where he tells us, <hi>That ſome were of opinion, That elder People ſhould be deferred Baptiſm, as well as Infants, agreeing therein, ſaith he, with the Anabaptiſts,</hi> (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199364:18"/> is our Cuſtom, waiting for fruits meet for Repentance in the firſt place, ſo deferring elder as well as younger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Council of <hi>Conſtant.</hi>
                     </note>And as to the Second, about the Canon of the Council of <hi>Conſtant.</hi> I find upon ſearch, that though the 2d Chapter, referred to by the <hi>Magd.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> mentions no more then what follows, <hi>viz. Si parvulus aegrotans ad quemlibet Presbyterum Baptiſmi gratia de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſlibet parochia allatus fuerit, ei Baptiſmi Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum nullo modo denegetur; ſiquis hoc munus petenti concedere detrectaverit, &amp; ille parvulus abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Baptiſmi gratia mortuus fuerit noverit ille qui eum non Baptizavit pro ejus anima rationem redditurum.</hi> Yet the 7th. Chapter which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point to, expreſſes what Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats from the <hi>Magd.</hi> about it; and withall, it does now appear alſo, that that 7th. Chapter is one of the 9 <hi>Binius</hi> reckons to be ſpurious, in theſe words, <hi>Hi novem ſequentes Canones falſo adſcribuntur ſextae Synedo; ſed quia pij cum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis eſſe videntur noluimus curioſum Lectorem eorum cognitione fraudare.</hi> Bin. Tom. 5. p. 361. And therefore upon the whole, though i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to clear me, that the omitting the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that place was not with an intention to deceive, having in my Book twice mentioned it; yet I acknowledge, it ſhould have been expreſt, or rather the whole quotation omitted, and do now diſown it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>That out of</hi> Calvins Inſtitutes.</note>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to that paſſage out of <hi>Calvins Inſtitutes,</hi> wherein I bring him <hi>p.</hi> 91. <hi>Treat.</hi> to confeſs, <hi>That it is no where expreſly mentioned by the Evangeliſts, that any one Child was by the Apoſtles hands Baptized;</hi> which he in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imates,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199364:18"/> was not <hi>Calvins</hi> ſence, but expreſt by him to have been the objection of Fools, the which Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> might bluſh to mention, when he knows <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf to own it as the next words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, <hi>viz. Et ſi enim id nominatim ab Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtis non narratur,</hi> i. e. <hi>For although it is not by the Evangeliſts expreſly mentioned:</hi> And is not that the making it his own? Concluding that their ſolly only lay in not receiving it, equivalent with Scripture, in as much as Infants were not excluded by Scripture,<note place="margin">Guilty of what he accuſeth.</note> and that whole Families are mentioned to be baptized: And therefore whether Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> did fairly in ſtopping his Tranſlation where he did (that it might appear to thoſe that underſtood not Latin to be ſo groſs as he would make it, and thereby render himſelf to be guilty of the very thing be falſly accuſeth me of, <hi>viz.</hi> To leave out part of the Author, that diſcovers he ſpeaks quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than he is made to ſpeak, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1.) is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Conſcience, and the conſiderate Reader.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to what he complains to have been left out in <hi>Bellarmin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4ly. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>and</hi> 6. <hi>Dr.</hi> Field.</note> viz. <hi>That Infants Baptiſm was to be deduced out of Scripture,</hi> p. 95. And that out of Dr. <hi>Field, That the grounds of it were taken out of Scripture,</hi> p. 155, 1. Ed. were alſo omitted from his own grounds aforeſaid: Becauſe I there quoted both of them under the Head of Tradition, (they both with ſo much poſitiveneſs aſſerting Infants Baptiſm ſo to be) yet you'l find, that when I ſpeak to that Head of <hi>Conſequences</hi> from Scripture, I quote them bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, as Reply, <hi>p.</hi> 74.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Dr. Owens.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>laſtly,</hi> As to that of Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> p. 175.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199364:19"/> which with <hi>Eſtius, Ainſworth</hi> and <hi>Ames,</hi> I brought to prove the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17.7. reſpected the Spiritual Seed only, <hi>viz.</hi> the Elect, who were to partake of the Spiritual Promiſes, (and not the Carnal Seed, as Paedo-baptiſts generally take it,) which the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. doth ſo fully and at large evince: And therefore that Clauſe he excepts againſt, was by his own Rule well enough left out, that ſpeaks to another thing. Though I confeſs, had I ſuppos'd that the omitting it, would have been any injury to the Dr. or juſt offence to any man, or any wrong to truth I ſhould have mentioned it, and which I may well do without any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the cauſe I maintain. For if I had been to prove that Circumciſion, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> External Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Covenant which the <hi>Jews</hi> had, belonged to their Carnal Seed, I ſhould have mentioned that; but in as much as the other was the matter in hand, I know not that it was ſo hainous to omit it, Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> in his own Caſe being Judge. It is our belief that (as the Dr. ſays) <hi>the external Adminiſtration of the Covenant, viz.</hi> Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cumciſion <hi>did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to</hi> Abraham, <hi>and his Carnal Seed</hi> (the Jews) under the legal Adminiſtration; yet it follows not therefore, that Baptiſm belongs to his Carnal Seed under the Goſpel Diſpenſation. And therefore the omitting that Phraſe, which is not at all diſputed betwixt us, could not be from any injurious deſign. And therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive I deſerve not the ſevere rebuke, he is pleaſed to give me for the ſame, <hi>viz. That I am therein guilty of much diſhoneſty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> 
                     <hi>and that it is ſuch an unworthy carriage, that be never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199364:19"/> the like in any man.</hi> Though truly if I ſhould have put it in, I know not what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> could make of it at another time, except he concludes, that the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ederal right to the Carnal Seed, is continued under the Goſpel, as it was under the Law, and gives the ſame right to claim the ſame priviledges now, as that did to the <hi>Jews</hi> before: If ſo, ſurely <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did greatly miſtake himſelf, when he forbad them <hi>Baptiſm</hi> upon that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, &amp; bids them not to ſay within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they were the Children of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> for that muſt not now ſerve their turns, it being only Fruits meet for Repentance, that that muſt qualifie them for the Baptiſm of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, (and Goſpel-Ordinances and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges) and not their old Carnal Priviledge to be <hi>Abrahams</hi> fleſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Seed, in which they mainly boaſted, &amp; whereon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey bolſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed themſelves. And ſutable he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eto doth Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> himſelf very excellently tell us in his 6. <hi>Exercit,</hi> on the <hi>Heb. p.</hi> 56 <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the miſapprehenſion hereof was the main thing that confirmed the</hi> Jews <hi>in their obſtinacy and unbelief, that being only a peculiar Priviledge to that fleſhly Seed, for the bringing forth of the Meſſiah into the World, and that when he was come, that Priviledge fell, and all Ordinances ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereto, expired, and new Ordinances of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip more ſuitable to the Goſpel were appointed,</hi> &amp;c. That whole <hi>Exercitation</hi> being written with ſo much <hi>Judgement</hi> and Spirituality, I would ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly recommend it to Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whiſtons</hi> Conſiderations, and all other of their <hi>minds,</hi> who would, upon like miſappreheſions,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199364:20"/> have Goſpel-Ordinances and Priviledges ſtill entailed upon the fleſhly Seed, upon that old federal right which was only Typical, as well obſerved to us, and done away, (having done its buſineſs) when Chriſt came into the world, that greater Priviledges, and better Ordinances ſuited to the Goſpel diſpenſation might take place. Jeſus Chriſt as the Dr. ſo well tells us in his <hi>Cat. p.</hi> 106. <hi>Requiring Regeneration as an indiſpenſible condition in a Member of his Church, a Subject of his Kingdom: For his Temple is now to be built of Living Stones,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. <hi>viz. Men ſpiritually, and ſavingly quickned, from their Death in ſin by the Holy Ghoſt, (whereof they are partakers) made a meet Habitation for God,</hi> Eph. 2.21, 22. 1 Cor. 3.16. 2 Cor. 6.16. &amp; pag. 103. <hi>God hath appointed Saints to be the ſeat and ſubject of all his Ordinances, having granted the right of them to them alone,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. But this by the By, which may not be unſeaſonable upon this occaſion. Thus I have diſpatch'd the firſt Head, not doubting but I have given am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſatisfaction therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II. His Second Complaint againſt me is,</hi> for adding to Authors<note place="margin">Adding to Authors.</note> without the Diſtinction of a different Character, whereof he gives ſeven Inſtances.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Anſwered. <hi>1.</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</note>This is a Charge that I think may concern moſt Writers, and 'tis confeſs'd, that many times it falls out, that through the inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of <hi>Writers,</hi> or careleſſneſs of <hi>Printers,</hi> that <hi>Quotations</hi> out of Authors are not alwayes written in a different <hi>Character,</hi> whereby the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199364:20"/> Reader is at a loſs many times, whether he reads his <hi>Author,</hi> or another Man that he refers to: And which is the fault, as Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> knows, of the <hi>Magdeburgs,</hi> of the <hi>Bazil</hi> Impreſſion, and the fault of Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his preſent Book, which I could abundantly evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence, if I would be Critical, and troub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the Reader with ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies. And wherein any ſuch omiſſion has been in any of my Writings, I can truly ſay they have not been wilful, but my trouble to find, and of which I ſhall be more careful for the future, and ſo will I hope my Corrector. But to be more particular to your 7 Inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe Two added to the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> are truly their own,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</hi>
                     </note> though not ſo immediately following in that Page. That other of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> was purely my own and ſhould have been diſtinguiſhed. That which he calls my adding to <hi>Jerom,</hi> poſitively ſaying they are none of his words, though I tell you, that he ſaith it is, is Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his grofs miſtake; for he will find they are his own words in his <hi>Annot.</hi> upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Tom.</hi> 9. <hi>Edit. Paris, Anno</hi> 1546. viz. <hi>Non enim poteſt fieri ut corpus Baptiſmi recipiat Sacramentum, niſi ante anima fidei ſuſceperit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem,</hi> i. e. <hi>For it cannot be, that the Body ſhould receive that Sacrament of Baptiſm, till the Soul hath before received the verity of Faith.</hi> That to <hi>Lydia</hi> is not an adding to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but my own ſenſe of the words, concluding, that only Believers in her Houſhold were Baptized, of which I ſpeak at large in my <hi>Reply,</hi> p. 184. That to <hi>Beza's</hi> is eaſily underſtood not to be his, by any ordinary Reader. And that to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199364:21"/> 
                     <hi>Ames</hi> very plainly. But what Injury done herein, and what the obſtinacy calling for an Appeal, is left to all to judge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Forgery.</note>
                     <hi>III. The Third Complaint is,</hi> For making Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors affirm one thing, when they affirm the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary, yea, contradicting my ſelf.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">Anſwered. <hi>1.</hi> About <hi>Eſtius.</hi>
                     </note>1. The firſt he mentions, is that of <hi>Eſtius</hi> for <hi>Calvin,</hi> heretofore owned by me, which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours nothing of Ingenuity, though in looking into my Book, I find I am not altogether ſo tardy as I took my ſelf to be; for whoever pleaſes to look <hi>p.</hi> 176. in the end of that Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, will find, that I put <hi>Eſtius Ann. Gen.</hi> 17.7. and by what miſtake <hi>Calvin</hi> came to be mentioned in the beginning of it, I know not, therefore how fair Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> was in that Cavil, and ſince, by his unmerciful inculcating the ſame, is left to the Reader.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Dr.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>on</hi> Joh. 13.10.</note>2. The ſecond is, for miſtaking, (as he ſaith) a Quotation out of Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> quite contrary to what he affirms, with his remark upon it, <hi>viz. No wonder Mr. D miſtakes Latin Authors ſo often, when he cannot rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe that are in Engliſh.</hi> But what cauſe there is for the ſame, and that it ought rather to be turned upon himſelf, will appear by the following Paralel.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199364:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Dan. Treat.</hi> p. <hi>194.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Dr. <hi>Hamonds</hi> An. <hi>on</hi> Joh. <hi>13.10. printed for</hi> R. Royſton, <hi>1653</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Mr.</hi> Wills <hi>ſaith, that Dr.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>ſaith,</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> upon <hi>Joh. 13.10</hi> tells us, that <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies an Immerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or waſhing the whole body, and which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> uſed for dipping in the Old Teſtament.</cell>
                           <cell>The <hi>Heb.</hi> had their <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, and their <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> the former, (<hi>viz.</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>) waſhing of the whole body, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, the other of the hands or feet, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying.</cell>
                           <cell>The <hi>Heb.</hi> had their <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, and their <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (that is <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>) the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole body, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, the other two (that is <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>) of the hands or feet.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then has the confidence to ſay, Mr. <hi>D. tells us, the Dr. ſaith</hi> Baptiſmos <hi>ſignifies an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſion, or waſhing of the whole Body, and anſwers to the Hebrew word</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>whereas indeed he tells us, That</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſignifies the waſhing of the whole Body, and anſwers to</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Now that this was exactly agreeable to the Drs. Writings elſewhere in the ſaid Book, as well as the truth, the Reader is deſired to peruſe him upon <hi>Mark</hi> 7.4. p. 172. where he ſaith, <hi>That the word</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>(as it differs from</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>which belongs to the hands or feet) ſignifies the waſhing of the whole body. Thus 'tis ſaid of Eupolis (which wrote the Tragedy called</hi> Baptae <hi>againſt</hi> Alcibiades) <hi>that being taken and thrown into the Sea</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and ſo the Baptiſms of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199364:22"/> Cups,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in the end of this Verſe is putting into water all over, rincing them: Two words there are uſed by the Hebrews for waſhing.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the word uſed for waſhing hands and feet onely, the</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>here; And</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>immerſion of the whole body, to which</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>anſwers.</hi> And upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1. p. 14. <hi>As the Jews call thoſe Lakes wherein they waſh themſelves</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſo in the Chriſtian Church the</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>or Veſſel which contained the Baptiſmal Water is oft called</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>a ſwimming or diving place.</hi>— And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>John in token of the reſolved change of the Jews, put them into the Water, and dipt them all over, and ſo took them out again; And upon the ſincerity of their change, promiſed them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins.</hi> And now whether it be Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> or I that have abuſed Mr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the unprejudiced Reader.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>3.</hi> About the Popes Name De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>dedit.</hi>
                     </note>As to the Third I grant, <hi>Deus dedit</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me two words, and not the Name of a Man; I rendred it <hi>Deo dans,</hi> or Gods gift, not conſidering, as Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> obſerves, that there had been a Pope of that Name, which ſince I find in the Catalogue of Popes, and therefore acknowledg it to be my error.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>4.</hi> Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of <hi>VValden.</hi>
                     </note>Fourthly, as to the Quotation out of <hi>Walden,</hi> I acknowledge Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> hath truly rectified to our advantage, which confirms more fully, that <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> and his followers, were againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm, in agreement with the <hi>Albegois,</hi> and <hi>Sylveſter</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> though different from <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Vicentius Victor,</hi> which was my miſtake, who (as it is ſaid) held Infants Baptiſm, and thereby reproved himſelf for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting the quite contrary, <hi>viz. That</hi> Walden
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199364:22"/> 
                     <hi>affirms, That</hi> Wickliffe <hi>held Infants Baptiſm,</hi> p. 45. of his <hi>Vind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words of <hi>Walden</hi> relating to <hi>Wickliffe</hi> are, <hi>Noſtri Wicliviſtae Baptiſmum Eccleſiaſticum inutile judicant parvulis,</hi> which <hi>[parvulis]</hi> Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> very unworthily leaves out, to inſinuate to his Reader, that they rejected all Baptiſm, whereas that term expreſly limits it to little ones; nor can I ſeriouſly conjecture, but its rather <hi>a lapſus mentis</hi> then <hi>error Calami</hi> or <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pographi:</hi> Nor does he take notice of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aſſigned there for their denying Infants Baptiſm, which is the very ſame Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> and thoſe of his mind, produce for its practice, <hi>viz. ſufficienter eos aiunt eſse mundatos &amp; ſanctos, quia de ſanctis parentibus &amp; Chriſtianis naſcuntur,</hi> i. e. <hi>They deem them ſufficiently cleans'd and holy, becauſe they are born of Holy and Chriſtian Parents.</hi> And now whether Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his Curtailing this Quotation, or my harmleſs and unndeſigned miſtake of aſſerting <hi>Wickliffe</hi> to agree with <hi>Pelagius</hi> be the more blameable, I humbly ſubmit to conſideration.</p>
                  <p>The Fifth is no contradiction,<note place="margin">5. <hi>That of</hi> 1. Cor. 7.14</note> which is only an Alluſion to thoſe in <hi>Ezra's</hi> time that put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their ſtrange Wives, Similies not running of all four, as Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> would ſtretch it.</p>
                  <p>The Sixth is no Contradiction,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>6.</hi> Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of <hi>Frank.</hi>
                     </note> for Infants Baptiſm might be univerſally received, and yet in many places little eſteemed, has it not been ſo heretofore here in <hi>England,</hi> as to that as well as other things I could mention? 1. Becauſe perſons may little eſteem things they receive. 2. By univerſal, I explain my ſelf to mean the Greek and Latin Churches, (which admitted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199364:23"/> of exception) <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe that ſubmitted to the Pope, and thoſe that were under the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>7.</hi> An Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of my own.</note>The Seventh is no Contradiction, which in the former Chapter I have ſo fully cleared; there being Antiquity for Believers Baptiſm in the firſt Centuries, but no Record for Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> grants, in the Church Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories. So that no primitive Antiquity for the ſame, though the Ancients in after Ages did aſſert it.</p>
                  <p>So that what ezceptions he has made hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, are but ſlender, and not of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor ſo perſiſted in, as to deſerve an Appeal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Falſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation.</note>
                     <hi>IV. He chargeth me with</hi> perverting the ſence of Authors by the falſeneſs of Tranſlations, whereof he gives Nine Inſtances.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p>Anſwered.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</p>
                     </note>As to Tranſlations, I conceive there is a great liberty allowed, provided the ſcope and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Author be well heeded; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> in his <hi>Defence,</hi> p. 16. <hi>Tranſlations are various, ſome affect in their Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations to follow their Author</hi> Kata poda, <hi>to have the very foot-ſteps of the words they tranſlate; other Tranſlations are Metaphraſtical, or by way of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe they expound as they tranſlate; thus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral men have their ſeveral fancies though they adhere to to the Author which they tranſlate, even when they keep not in all things to his words;</hi> Jerom <hi>gives Inſtances in the Septuagint tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe Teſtimony I need not name to you.</hi> But to the particulars.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199364:23"/>
                  <p>As to the <hi>firſt</hi> of <hi>Bullingers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
                     </note> I did not tranſlate it, but tranſcribed it word for word out of that Author, called, <hi>A very plain and well grounded Treatiſe concerning Baptiſm.</hi> p. 14. mentioned by me p. 9. It is true, I confeſs, I ſhould have expreſt it, or rather have ſearch'd the original my ſelf, and ſo ſhould Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> when he ſo miſtakenly quoted one from Dr. <hi>Holmes,</hi> and did neither, and another from the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> about <hi>Eraſmus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to the Second, about <hi>Nazianzen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen.</note> 
                     <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zandos peccatae ſua confiteri ſolitos,</hi> I own it ſhould be rendred, <hi>The Baptized were wont to confeſs their ſins.</hi> Nor did I give it as a tranſlation, <hi>verbatim;</hi> but what I apprehended to be the conſequential ſence, which I deduce thus: [the <hi>Baptized</hi>] being an indefinite term, and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polent with an univerſal, is as much, as if all the Baptized did ſo; and if all did confeſs their ſins, then none but ſuch we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Baptized in the firſt times, which is concurrent with the ſence of ſo many Authors, ſo poſitively affirming the ſame thing; and if that be not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I humbly conceive the expreſſion (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood) may be ſomewhat imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, it being owned of all hands, that the Adult in all Ages ſo to do.</p>
                  <p>The Third is of <hi>Olympiodorus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>Olympi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus.</hi>
                     </note> a meer quibble, and catching at words; the word [Born] by the words going before, <hi>viz.</hi> Spiritual Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, being eaſily underſtood to be [born again] however the word [again] came to be omitted.</p>
                  <p>The Fourth of <hi>Albertus,</hi> is of like Import;<note place="margin">4. <hi>Albertus</hi>
                     </note> for if Baptiſm cannot through the incapacity of the ſubject operate upon them, it may be truly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199364:24"/> ſaid in a Paraphraſtical Tranſlation, That it is not proper to admit Infants thereto: For if it cannot operate in any other but the Adult, who are illuminated and called, who can draw Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from Chriſts Death and Reſurrection, then Baptiſm not proper for other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">5. <hi>Albinus.</hi>
                     </note>Neither is the Fifth from <hi>Albinus</hi> ill rendred or perverting the ſence if you take the ſcope, and former words, which ſpeak the thing he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts againſt; and which Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> leaves out, a liberty being granted to paraphraſe, keeping to the ſence, though contracting the words.</p>
                  <p>The Sixth is no perverting or miſ-repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Magdeb.</hi> in ſaying, They tell us, That in the latter end of the Fourth <hi>Cent.</hi> they Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Children, giving it from the teſtimony of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> who writ in the latter part of the 4th. <hi>Cent.</hi> That <hi>Contra Arianos</hi> being writ, as ſaith <hi>Helvicus, Anno</hi> 360 But I have ſince made appear, that the <hi>Magdeb.</hi> tell us therein an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; for that pretended account was from <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s ſuppoſed Queſtions, which they themſelves afterwards confeſs to be ſpurious, as I have told Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> and he confeſſeth to be true, and therefore wonder, that he ſhould have the Confidence to put this under the notion of miſ-repreſentation, or miſ-tranſlation, it being neither. Had I given a tranſlation of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the ſentence, reſpecting <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> (before refuted by me, and which I cencern'd not with my ſelf, then) and not rende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d [in <hi>Eccleſiijs Affricaenis</hi>] in the <hi>Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Churches, there might be ſome ground of <hi>Cavil;</hi> but whereas I did not, I hope I may be excus'd. The words are, <hi>Hoc vero ſeculo eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199364:24"/>
[viz. Baptiſmum] <hi>duraſse ex</hi> Athanaſio <hi>conſtat, quaeſt.</hi> 124. i. e. <hi>It appears from</hi> Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius 124. <hi>queſtion, that it</hi> (viz. Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) <hi>was in this Age.</hi> So that what I ſay reſpects the time, and not whether all or part of the <hi>Affrican</hi> Churches. But if to ſay in the <hi>Affrican</hi> Churches they Baptized Children, pleaſes Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> I am contented it ſhould be ſo; and let him make the moſt of it.</p>
                  <p>The 7th. concerning the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Decree,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>7.</hi> About the <hi>Milevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> Canon.</note> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> That firſt part of the Canon, <hi>That all that affirm, that young Children receive Everlaſting life, albeit they be not by the Sacrament of Grace or Baptiſm renewed.</hi> I made it not, nor abuſed that Council, nor miſ-tranſlated their words, for in the Verſe before going, as the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> expreſs it, <hi>p.</hi> 835. they repreſent the crime of thoſe they cenſure in theſe words, <hi>Non opitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari parvulis ad conſequendam vitam Aeternam Chriſtianae gratiae Sacramentum,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Criſtian Grace</hi> (or Baptiſm) <hi>profits not little Children to Everlaſting Life.</hi> The ſame alſo is expreſt by the whole Council to <hi>Innocentius,</hi> in their Synodical Epiſtle, <hi>p.</hi> 842. in theſe words, <hi>pueros qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> parvulos ſi nullis innoventur, &amp; gratiae Sacramentis, habituros vitam Aeternam.</hi> The ſame is alſo in <hi>Innocents Decretal Letter,</hi> p. 845. <hi>which he reiurned to the Council</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Illud vero quod eos veſtra fraternitas aſſerit praedicare, parvulos Aeternae Vitae praemijs, etiam ſine Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis gratia, poſſe donari perfatuum eſt;</hi> And to meet with thoſe Hereticks, (as they counted them) was the decree I mentioned, made, and which is to be found in <hi>Regia Collect. Tom.</hi> 4. p. 559. immediately after the words recited
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199364:25"/> by Mr. <hi>Wills ex Pervetuſto codices,</hi> out of a very ancient Copy, thus. <hi>Item placuit, ut ſiquis dicit ideo dixiſſe Dominum, in domo patris mei manſiones multae ſunt, ut intelligatur, quia in regno Caelorum erit aliquis medius, aut ullus alicubi lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, ubi beate vivant parvuli, qui ſine Baptiſmo ex hac vita migrarunt, ſine quo in regno Caelorum quod eſt vita aeterna intrare non poſsunt Anathema ſit;</hi> and which is the very thing I affirmed: and therefore I hope will juſtifie me from this Charge, giving onely an Epitome, and not the whole of the Decree, out of the Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals themſelves, not the <hi>Magdeburgs.</hi> 'Tis true, the Canon has not this <hi>Appendix</hi> to it, where recited by the <hi>Magdeburgs,</hi> nor in <hi>Reg. Collect.</hi> p. 362. though properly belonging to it; but where the <hi>Affrican</hi> Canons are <hi>collected, repeated,</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> under <hi>Caeleſtinus</hi> Pope, and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> Emperor, <hi>Anno</hi> 424. it is annext. And then this 2d. Canon of the <hi>Milevitan Council,</hi> with this annexed, is made the 77th <hi>Affrican</hi> Canon. And I muſt further inform the Reader, that the <hi>Mag'd.</hi> confounded theſe two <hi>Milevitan</hi> Councils to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, putting the latter, which was in the year 416, under the year 402. which was the firſt <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council in <hi>Numidia</hi> in <hi>Affrica;</hi> and both held under <hi>Innocent</hi> Pope, and <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> Emperor; which miſtake is taken notice of in <hi>Regia Collectione,</hi> with the grounds thereof. And in p. 541. you'l find theſe words begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Collection, <hi>Sequuntur Concilia Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricana ſub Innocentio habita:</hi> which includes the Canon I cite in p. 559. aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> About P. <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents</hi> Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</note>That the 8th. is no miſ-repreſentation, in ſaying, That <hi>P. Innocentius attributed divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199364:25"/> to the Popedom,</hi> will be eaſily conceived, inaſmuch, as he ſingled out <hi>Peter,</hi> and attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Divine Honour to him, put confidence in him, and deſired help from him in conjunction with God himſelf; and whether he did it as to Pope <hi>Peter,</hi> or St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is not much material, the former is probable. And therefore doth <hi>Fox</hi> 2 <hi>Vol. p.</hi> 1020. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tell us in how many things the Popes blaſphemouſly match them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with God himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The 9th. out of <hi>Voſſius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>9.</hi> Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of <hi>Voſſius.</hi>
                     </note> giving the Reaſons from the Ancients, why they Baptized Men and Women naked, is a full and clear Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as fully made good from thoſe particular inſtances given out of <hi>Voſſius</hi> from <hi>Cyril, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, Cretenſis, Anſelm, Ambroſe,</hi> &amp;c. his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a miſerable trifle in his Appeal to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether the Reaſons given, were not <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their naked Bodies were to be Baptized, and not the Cloaths,</hi> as I <hi>ignorantly</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>affirm,</hi> whereas I give thoſe Reaſons, <hi>why they Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized their naked Bodies, and not the Cloaths,</hi> viz. <hi>That they might be, as in the ſtate of Innocency;</hi> and as in their <hi>firſt Birth,</hi> and as they expect to be in <hi>Heaven,</hi> or as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was was <hi>nailed to the Croſs.</hi> From the Ancients, which they expreſly make out in <hi>p.</hi> 32.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it is left to the Reader to judge, where there is the leaſt miſ-repreſentation, or falſe Tranſlation in all theſe Particulars, and what cauſe to make an Appeal for the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <hi>V.<note place="margin">Forgery.</note> The Fifth thing he complains againſt me for is,</hi> For fathering upon Authors that which they indeed ſay not, at leaſt in the places, by me quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>whereof he gives 8 Inſtances.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:199364:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Anſwered. <hi>1:</hi> Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </note>The firſt as to a Quotation out of <hi>Luther de Sacrament. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 168. I tranſcribed it out of the ſame Author before mentioned, <hi>the plain and well grounded Treatiſe,</hi> p. 25. I have ſince examined that <hi>Tome,</hi> but cannot there find it; ſuppoſing, they either miſquoted the <hi>Tome,</hi> or elſe quoted it out of another Edition, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſo large a Quotation was not fathered upon him, he ſpeaking much that Language in other places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Out of <hi>Bazil.</hi>
                     </note>To the Second, as to the Quotation of <hi>Bazil, contra Eunom.</hi> who only ſay, That he ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>That Baptiſm is the Seal of Faith.</hi> But he will find the reſt of the Sentence in that Book of <hi>Bazil</hi> they refer to, <hi>viz. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p</hi> 84. <hi>Baptiſm is the Seal of Faith; but Faith, the Confeſſion of the Deity: for firſt he ought to believe, and after to be ſealed with Baptiſm.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Nam cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere prius oportet ac poſtea Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignari.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">3. Magdeb.</note>To the Third, where he ſaith, <hi>That the</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburgs <hi>do not ſay, it was the univerſal practiſe to Baptize the Adult under the</hi> 4th. <hi>Cent. as I affirm they do.</hi> I ſay, That I have made it appear, they do by thoſe Inſtances mentioned by them, from the ſayings of the Doctors, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Councils, that Decreed only for Adult Baptiſm; and for which, I refer you to the former Chapter for further proof, that I did not miſ-repreſent them therein. If I ſpeak their ſence, though vary in words, and contract what they ſay at large, I do them no injury. But ſo they do expreſs it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">4. Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius.</note>To the 4th, That I quote <hi>Arnobius,</hi> a ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Author, whilſt I blame him for ſuch, and which I ſay, I take out of the <hi>Magd.</hi> whereas the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> have it not.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199364:26"/>
                  <p>To which I ſay firſt, I do not know, that <hi>Arnobius</hi> upon the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> is a ſpurious Author, ſhould I have quoted him out of <hi>Perkins,</hi> who (Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> ſaith) tells us, it is ſpurious, as he did <hi>Athanaſius's</hi> queſtions out of the <hi>Magdeb.</hi> which they ſaid was ſo, I had been lyable to like Reproof. Neither 2dly. did I ſay, I took <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> out of the <hi>Magdeburgs;</hi> I ſaid the <hi>Magd.</hi> did give ſome of thoſe that followed, not all, he being mentioned upon the 146. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and not from any Book or Page in the <hi>Magdeburgs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Fifth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>5.</hi> Out of <hi>Aquinus.</hi>
                     </note> it is true, is a miſtake as placed by the Printer, but not intended, as eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd by the Reader, being put down as an additional Proof out of <hi>Albertus,</hi> having In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted 3 before, the Printer putting <hi>Aquinus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt of them, and ſo made that which I had put, <hi>viz.</hi> [And again] to belong to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinus,</hi> and not to <hi>Albertus.</hi> Which Venial miſtake he makes equivolent with that grand one of <hi>Bazil</hi> for <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> which he ſo egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly abuſed me for, and boaſted what great acquaintance he had with Father <hi>Bazil,</hi> putting it down as a great remark 3 ſeveral times: This of mine being a proof for him, <hi>viz.</hi> to prove Infants Baptiſm; therefore it matters not much, whether from one or the other, they both ſpeaking the ſame thing, that of his, wholly againſt me.</p>
                  <p>As to the 6th. the <hi>Magd.</hi> tell us,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>6.</hi> Out of the <hi>Magd.</hi>
                     </note> That Infants as well as the Adult, were Baptized; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance onely in a Queen then Baptized, whom <hi>Zonaras</hi> calls <hi>Roſſorum Reginam.</hi> And that's all (I confeſs) that <hi>Zonaras</hi> is concern'd in it.</p>
                  <p>The 7th. is ſuch another trifle. I ſay,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>7.</hi> Out of <hi>Voſſius.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Voſſius</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199364:27"/> ſaith, (for he was a Collector from Authors; and thoſe he quotes, we may in propriety of ſpeech attribute to him) That <hi>Nectarius</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> before he was Baptized, he ſays, he was but appointed ſo, the ſtreſs of the proof lying, That he was a Believer at age before he was Baptized, there being no ſuch great difference, betwixt being made and appointed Biſhop in the Caſe. And <hi>Beza</hi> there gives inſtances, not of obſcure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but of perſons, as he ſays, that had the eyes of all upon them Baptized at Age, <hi>viz. Conſtantine, Nectarius,</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>8.</hi> One of Mr. B.</note>The 8th. is much like his fellows, in a Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> proving againſt the Popiſh Doctrine, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> to work Grace by the deed done, I brought him to ſay, <hi>That Baptiſm of it ſelf cannot give Grace or Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor can work any ſuch cauſe; for Water, he ſaith, is not a ſubject either capable of receiving or conveying Grace to the Soul.</hi> But he ſaith, I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> words, who ſaith, <hi>That Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm can be no ſuch cauſe, whereby I do, as he ſaith, attribute Non-ſence and Abſurdity to him; and that there is neither Innocency nor Truth in ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing it. If to work no ſuch cauſe,</hi> be ſuch an error, it is a venial one, and I can ſay, not wilful; but certainly this Man would make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table work with me, if he had matter to work upon. But what juſt cauſe of Complaint or Appeal in all this, I profeſs ſeriouſly, I ſee not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Miſplacing Quotations</note>
                     <hi>VI. The</hi> 6th <hi>is, for picking out of</hi> Authors here and there, and joyning them together, as if they were one intire Sentence, whereof he gives four Inſtances.</head>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199364:27"/>
                  <p>To the 3 firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſwered.</note> and Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> I ſay, I have put down nothing but their own, and what is congruous, one thing anſwering properly and naturally with another, which if it did not, we ſhould, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, have heard of.</p>
                  <p>And for what relates to himſelf, which is the 4th. I have done him no wrong, the Pages men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by me, <hi>viz.</hi> p. 36, 38, 101, 131, 132. I have particularly examined, and deſire the Reader ſo to do; and let him judge betwixt us, whether he doth not in thoſe Pages compared again and again ſay, <hi>That as there is no Scripture expreſly commanding, ſo neither is there any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture excluding Infants from Baptiſm, nor any Scripture that ſaith, there was no Infant Baptized,</hi> each Page I would have put down, but that I would not burden the Reader; which you find expreſt by me in my <hi>Reply,</hi> p. 63. and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pages particularly expreſt, I refer to. And what good cauſe is given to complain of me in this, I ſee as little as the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VII. The</hi> 7th. <hi>is,</hi> for aſſerting notorious untruths,<note place="margin">Notorious untruths.</note> giving Inſtances of Eight.</head>
                  <p>The firſt for affirming,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>That Antiquity it ſelf, ſo much boaſted of, is altogether for Believers, and not for Infants Baptiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> About Antiquity for Infant Baptiſm.</note> an Aſſertion, as he ſaith, ſo <hi>notoriouſly falſe,</hi> that I have <hi>confuted my ſelf in owning the ancients aſserted it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is already anſwered again and again, I hope to ſatisfaction, <hi>viz. That primitive Antiquity is only for Believers, and not for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm; and the Ancients in latter, not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199364:28"/> former Centuries, onely for Infants Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> About Chriſtning a Dead Child.</note>The Second for ſaying, <hi>That a Child that dyed unbaptized, was taken up and Chriſtned, putting in the Margent a dead Child Chriſtned; the Boy was not taken up and Baptized Dead; but after he came to life again, he was Baptized.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the firſt place, I conceive there is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth in my rendring the words, <hi>Is puerum ſine Baptiſmo mortuum reſuſcitarit ex mortuis, &amp; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Baptizarit, That a Child that dyed unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, was taken up and Chriſtned;</hi> being not excluſive of the ſence Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> would have it bear. But 'tis the Margent that ſaith <hi>[a dead Child Chriſtned]</hi> he mainly quarrels at, which indeed is wholly mine, and therefore my ſence or explanation of my own words, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, which admits of a Two fold, or double Interpretation, <hi>viz.</hi> either that Child that was Dead, now Chriſtned, and ſo not to be blamed in Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> own ſence: Or if I ſhould intend the Child then dead when Chriſtned, I know no reaſon, but I may have my liberty of Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, as well as Mr. <hi>Wills:</hi> And the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though <hi>reſuſcitare</hi> be generally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, <hi>to raiſe to life,</hi> yet the phraſe here, may, without any ſuch palpable abſurdity, be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, a taking up from among the Dead, or out of the Grave; eſpecially, becauſe ſuch an Interpretation ſo exactly agrees with their (then uſual) practiſe to Baptize the Dead that dyed unbaptized; which certainly is more likely, and far more agreeable to truth, then that ſuch a Miracle was wrought of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to life. Beſides, why may not the Dead be ſometimes uſed for the Grave, as the Grave
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199364:28"/> is often (Metonymically) uſed for the Dead, and Death? as I could inſtance with great variety, had it been neceſſary. So that this latter (ſhould I perſiſt in it) is ſo far from being blameable, that it is indeed very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and therefore Reader, take it which way you will, no ſuch notorious untruth as he talks of can hence be juſtly chargeable upon me.</p>
                  <p>The third noto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ious untruth he ſaith I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, is from the <hi>Magdeburgs,</hi> Cent: 13. <hi>p:</hi> 419. <hi>viz. That the</hi> Magd: <hi>do ſay,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>3</hi> About <hi>Gulielmus</hi> blaſphemy.</note> 
                     <hi>that as to the form of Baptiſm,</hi> Gulielmus <hi>added to the Father. Son, and Holy Spirit, the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>viz. I baptize thee in the Name of the Omnipotent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Spirit, and the Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary; which ſaith he, is another notorious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; for the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> ſay nothing of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> but which of us ſpeak truth, let the Reader judge: The words of the <hi>Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs</hi> are theſe in the <hi>Cent:</hi> and <hi>p:</hi> above-ſaid, <hi>viz: Male</hi> Gulielmus <hi>ad Formam Baptiſmi addidit</hi> Mariam,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Baptizo te in Nomine Patris Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis, &amp; Filii &amp; Spiritus Sancti, &amp; Beatae</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae <hi>Virginis.</hi> De Bapt: &amp; ejus part. c. 2. Magd. Cent: 13. c: 419. <hi>i: e.</hi> Gulielmus <hi>wickedly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> Mary <hi>to the form of Baptiſm: I Baptize thee in the Name of the Omnipotent Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, and the Bleſſed</hi> Virgin Mary in his 2. <hi>ch:</hi> of Bapt. and its parts. Therefore if this be not daring temerity, I know not what is.</p>
                  <p>To the 4th. that the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>4</hi> About the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>is as true, as that a Dead Child was Baptized, and that Pope</hi> Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>was the firſt Inventor of Baptiſm, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity altogether for Believers, and not for Infants Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199364:29"/>
                  <p>What ground I had to affirm the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were againſt Infants Baptiſm, I have given at large enough at leaſt, if not to make it good, yet to free me from a Forger. Whether the Child taken up was living or dead, when Baptized (what I writ being capable of being i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>terpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either way) is left to better judgment; that I any where have ſaid that Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> was the firſt Invetor of Infants Baptiſm, is I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> his Invention not to be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e good from my writings. I do indeed ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 111. And this was that <hi>Innocent</hi> who was the firſt great Patron and Impoſer of this Inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>viz.</hi> In his Canon in the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; and ſo ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Dr. <hi>Taylor Grotius, Strabo,</hi> p. 107. as well as my ſelf, that Infants Baptiſm was never determined, nor en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyned nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed till th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. And whether Antiqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, <hi>viz.</hi> of the firſt Centuries was not for Be ievers, and not for Infants Baptiſm; Let Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, wi h what hath been ſaid, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ermine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">5 <hi>About</hi> Lanfrank.</note>The 5th about <hi>Lanfranks</hi> Teſtimony, one of my witneſſes to prove <hi>Berengarius</hi> denyed Infants Baptiſm, is, I fully acknowledg my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, which (a Perſon of quality) a worthy Friend of mine ſeveral moneths ſince help'd me to diſcover, in examining that Story of <hi>Berengarius</hi> with me out of the <hi>Magdeburgs,</hi> and who is my witneſs of my in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ended reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to rectifie the ſame, and which I conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to have done, though not diſcovered by them. And the ground of that my miſtake was truly this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I finding that in the Hypotheſis of the erroneous Dogm's charged upon <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius;</hi> they gather up 5 or 6 Particulars, the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199364:29"/> firſt 4 reſpecting Tranſubſtantiation, the 5th. and 6th. Infants Baptiſm, and Marriage, then ſuperficially caſting my Eye to the end of the Story, I found it ſaid, <hi>ad quintum &amp; ſextum op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit Doctrinam perpetuam &amp; conſenſientem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Dei, To the</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. and 6th. <hi>he therein oppoſes the perpetual and agreeing Doctrine of the Church of God;</hi> Quoting <hi>Lanfrank</hi> of the Sacraments, and his Book <hi>de Scintill:</hi> concluding it did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect thoſe 5 or 6 Particulars before mentioned, but afterwards examining it with the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Friend, I found that thoſe 5 or 6 Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars did not include thoſe firſt mentioned, but were 6 other Particulars diſcourſed about Tranſubſtantiation, betwixt <hi>Lanfrank</hi> and him Yet this I muſt remark by the way, that though I miſtook my ſelf in this, yet the reſt of my Teſtimonies to prove <hi>Berengarius</hi> did deny In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm hold good, as you'l find before in <hi>p.</hi> 92. 2d. <hi>Rep. Guitmond</hi> being one of them, who aſſerts that he did affirm Baptiſm did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit little ones.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. As to the Canon of <hi>Illerdon</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">7 Illerdon <hi>Canon.</hi>
                     </note> I quote it out of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Book of Martyrs, for which they Cite their Authorities at large, <hi>page</hi> 189. 1 <hi>Book.</hi> And if they have miſtaken it, let them be accountable for it, and me, no more than Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> deſires to be, for quoting the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> in their miſtake about <hi>Eraſmus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Amongſt my notorious untruths he puts <hi>my calling Circumciſion a legal Ordinance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>6</hi> About Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin.</note> 
                     <hi>when as he ſaith, it was inſtituted</hi> 400 <hi>Years before the Law.</hi> VVhat then? ſo were Sacrifices 2000 Years before it; were they not therefore le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal alſo, being enjoyned by God as well as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199364:30"/> the other under the Law? and therefore 'tis ſaid <hi>of Circumciſion, though of the Fathers, yet it was given by</hi> Moſes, <hi>John</hi> 7.22. and which was ſo <hi>legal,</hi> that it bound to the keeping of the whole Law, <hi>Gal:</hi> 2.3. and ſo <hi>typical</hi> and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowy, that it was to be done away when Chriſt came, <hi>Gal:</hi> 2.2. and of ſuch <hi>great ſtreſs</hi> that there was no entring into the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church without it, &amp; whoever eat the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uncircumciſed muſt be cut off: And that the Paedo-Baptiſts Arguments from Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are begged, not proved: See my <hi>Reaſons</hi> p: And how all my Arguments are begg'd or ſtollen, is begging ſtill till proved, which will be beſt underſtood by his Anſwers, to which theſe are referred.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <note place="margin">Sericius, <hi>for</hi> Hinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marus.</note>8: The miſtake of the name <hi>Sericius</hi> for <hi>Hincmarus</hi> I own; but what Decrees were made by <hi>P: Sericius</hi> ſo immediatly proceeding <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> for Infants Baptiſm as Mr: <hi>Wills</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, I find not, when he produceth them I'll blot out <hi>Innocent,</hi> and put <hi>Sericius</hi> the firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="complaint">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Strange Doctrines.</note>
                     <hi>VIII.</hi> The laſt he charges is ſtrange Doctrines.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt for calling the National Church of the</hi> Jews,<note place="margin">
                        <p>Anſwered.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1</hi> About the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church.</p>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>made up of the Carnal Seed, a Carnal Church, who had Carnal Ordinances, which</hi> he ſaith is <hi>Blaſphemy to affirm.</hi> But that Balſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the Holy Spirit will acquit me of whilſt he calls their Ordinances of their Church by that Name, and what <hi>Salvo</hi> Mr: <hi>Wills</hi> gives for their Ordinances, will ſerve for the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>which is to be underſtood</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively;</hi> and ſo ſay I to the more Spiritua
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199364:30"/> Church and Ordinances in the New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>But that Baptiſm doth as much Initiate the carnal ſeed in the Goſpel-Church, as circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion under the Law, is I preſume Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> ſtrange Doctrine, God enjoyning the Infant-male or Carnal Seed to be circumciſed; but ſo hath he not that under the Goſpel they ſhould be baptized: and touching which I refer you to Dr: <hi>Owen</hi> for better Information, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Falſe Doctrine,</hi> That <hi>I do with Dr.</hi> Taylor <hi>ſay, Infants have neither Habitual nor actuall Faith, nor are Diſciples of Chriſt, and uncapable of Regeneration,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2</hi> About Infants Faith and Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo conſequently of Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That they are uncapable of that Faith and Regeneration ſpoken by <hi>James</hi> 1.18. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>John</hi> 1.12, 13. And as Dr: <hi>Owen</hi> has defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Regeneration is all I ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> begotten by the <hi>Preaching, Hearing,</hi> and <hi>Receiving of the Word,</hi> renewed in knowledg, changed and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted thereby,</hi> is all that I affirm, <hi>page</hi> 213. That they are capable of Salvation by Chriſts purchaſe and the Application of his Blood and Spi it to them, who doubts it? I am ſure I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver affirmed the cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The next falſe Doctrine is for <hi>affirming nothing to be a Seal of the New Covenant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>3</hi> Baptiſm no ſeal.</note> 
                     <hi>but the Holy Spirit, a ſtrange Paradox!</hi> But when Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> or any body elſe proves the contrary, I ſhall be content to alter my judgment.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>That Infants are neither capable to perform Duties,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>4</hi> Infants capacity.</note> 
                     <hi>nor enjoy Priviledges, viz.</hi> Church-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, as I have ſufficiently explained my ſelf <hi>page viz. Baptiſm, Lords Supper Hearing the Word, Church-watch, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:199364:31"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>5</hi> About Baptiſm.</note>5. <hi>For owning Baptiſm to be the gate of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> viz. <hi>ini ſenſu ſano viz.</hi> The firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Church, where the Holy things in Chriſts order and way are duly adminiſtred, not in the Popiſh ſenſe of Sacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>6</hi> New Teſt. Church.</note>6. <hi>That the New-Teſtament Church is by Chriſts appointment to be a ſeparated people, conſiſting only of the Spiritual Seed of</hi> Abraham; but he ſaith, <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>wicked perſons are in it.</hi> But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will he call that Chriſts, or the Devil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, who ſows the Tares? of which Point Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> has well ſpoke, to whom I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him as before.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>7</hi> About the Order of Baptiſm.</note>7. <hi>That the Myſtery ſhould go before tht Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol.</hi> Had Mr: <hi>Ws.</hi> repreſented the quotation truly, the very peruſing it would clear me from this charge; but he (very unworthily) leaves out the Parentheſis which explicates the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and without which the words ſeem to import, a harſh Doctrine. The words a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, <hi>If the Myſtery goes not before the Symbol, (which it does when the Symbols are conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Grace, as the Sacraments are) [this Parentheſis he lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es out] yet it alwayes accompanies it, but never follows in order of time</hi> I do not deny but a man may be Baptized if he profe es Faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance though not in truth, and in him the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery goes not before the Symbol; but coming afterwards really to believe and repent, it may follow in order of time, but then the Symbol to him when Baptized was no conſignation of Grace. And now let the world judge whether Mr: <hi>Ws.</hi> dealt honeſtly in skiping over thoſe words which were laid in on purpoſe to obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199364:31"/> ſuch a Cavil as he makes; it may be truly ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him, that if he cannot find a hole, he'll make one.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>No viſible Church-member before Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>8.</hi> About Church-Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</note> I ſay none ought to be ſo, and ſo ſaith Dr: <hi>Owen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>That I make a Believer and Dipping to be the right matter and form of Baptiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>9.</hi> About the matter and form of Faptiſm.</note> which I have proved againſt Mr: <hi>Blinman,</hi> and neither by Mr: <hi>Wills</hi> nor him yet anſwered.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 <hi>That nothing now but Fruits meet for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>10.</hi> About receiving to Baptiſm.</note> 
                     <hi>can give right to the baptiſm of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and nothing ſhort of the Spirits birth can or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly admit to Water-baptiſm, and Spiritual Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, a Doct ine apparently falſe, inſtancing in</hi> John, <hi>baptizing the</hi> Jews <hi>upon confeſſion of ſin and repentance, which was not Fruits, and the</hi> 3000 <hi>Baptized.</hi> Acts 2. And were they not prick'd at heart, and received the word gladly, and confeſt Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> whom they and were not thoſe Fruits meet for Repentance and amen ment of life? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>THE CONCLUSION</head>
                  <p>THus I have given a <hi>Candid</hi> return to each Particular charged in this <hi>Appeal,</hi> publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledging what of Error or Miſtake I am convinced of, and juſtifying my Innocency and Integrity in the reſt; for as yet I ſee cauſe to own no more (not accounting a few imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial over ſights which Ingenious men would ſcorn to dwell upon) than the miſ-naming two or three, <hi>viz. Aquinas</hi> for <hi>Albertus, Sericius</hi> for <hi>Hincmarus,</hi> not hitting the Pope <hi>Deus dedit's</hi> name, and not taking a Quotation out of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199364:32"/> 
                     <hi>Walden</hi> to ſo good advantage as I ought, that of <hi>Auſtin</hi> 3 and 4 Book being left out, <hi>Lanfrank</hi> being before owned to Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concluding that as none of which can be ſuppoſed to be wilful, ſo neither can there be any obſtinacy in the Caſe, having never heard of them before.</p>
                  <p>Therefore upon the whole, I joyn iſſue with Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> freely ſubmitting it to the Bar he has brought it; not doubting upon the due examination of his Complaint, and my defence, that if they find me guilty of the Crimes he lays to my Charge; but they will, as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, diſcharge duty to me as becomes them, to bring me to the acknowledgment of my evil, or to diſown me if obſtinate, as a perſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be countenanced amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>But if on the contrary Mr: <hi>Wills</hi> his Appeal appears to be faulty, and the Particulars there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of not true, then that his ſaid Appeal ſhall, as he deſires, as unjuſt, reflect the blame of the charge upon himſelf, according to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Law of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Deut: 19.16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>If a falſe Witneſs riſe up againſt any man, and teſtifie againſt him that which is wrong, then both the men before whom the Controverſie is, ſhall ſtand before the Lord, and the Judges which ſhall be in thoſe dayes. And the Judges ſhall make diligent inquiſition; and behold if the witneſs be a falſe witneſs, and hath teſtified falſely againſt his Brother, then ſhall ye do unto him as he had thought to have done unto his Brother: So ſhalt thou put the evil away from amongſt you: And thoſe that remain ſhall hear, and fear, and ſhall henceforth commit no more any ſuch evil among you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199364:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> An Appeal to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Will</hi>'s Conſcience.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Having at your <hi>Groundleſs</hi> and injurious ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, given this full <hi>Account</hi> of my ſelf, in my juſt <hi>vindication:</hi> And ſo far as I am <hi>convinced</hi> made (as you charitably ſuggeſt I would, <hi>Pref. App.</hi>) a <hi>Candid</hi> and publick acknowledgment of what of <hi>error</hi> or miſtake is made out againſt me by your ſelf or others, may therefore with more freedom <hi>apply</hi> to your Conſcience herein, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince I offer you <hi>nothing,</hi> but what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive carries demonſtration with it, and back'd with <hi>Scripture evidence,</hi> for your better conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and conviction.</p>
               <p>Therefore in the firſt place, I deſire you to conſider, whether you are not notoriouſly guilty of <hi>Back-biting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Reproach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full Back-biting.</note> by taking up reproaches from others, and <hi>Tale-bearer</hi> like, ſpreading and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the <hi>ſame</hi> to the defaming your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, without enquiring into the Truth <hi>thereof</hi> from himſelf; nay, refuſing all due <hi>information</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> when friendly tendred to you.</p>
               <p>For, have you not taken up theſe following things upon report and <hi>Hear-ſay</hi> from others, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one that is a meer ſtranger to you, &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the ſame to my diſgrace, to promote thereby your Cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That, as you have heard, <hi>I own not ſo much Scholarſhip to compoſe ſuch a Book, though my
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199364:33"/> ſolitary life has given me opportunity enough to ſtudy,</hi> Pref. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That <hi>I have only fixed my Name to the Book, that another chiefly has moſt Reaſon to own himlſelf to be the Author of,</hi> Pref. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>That, as you have heard, I have</hi> Ixion <hi>like, faln in love with my own ſhaddow, puft up with the Excellency of my own performance,</hi> Ibid.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That <hi>I am a very tenacious Perſon, as you have heard,</hi> Vind. P.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That <hi>I am fain to call in the Wits of our Party, to help me to deal with you,</hi> Pref. Vind.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, That <hi>I am of a Self-conceited ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Genius, unbecoming a Chriſtian,</hi> Infants Bapt. a g. 86.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Inſinuating that <hi>I am of ſuch a (pugnatious or) fighting temper, that though my hands are tied behind me, yet will do it with Tongue and Pen,</hi> Pref. Inf. Bapt.</p>
               <p>But, how agreeable ſuch actings are with the following Scriptures, I leave you to judge.</p>
               <p>Exod. 23.1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not receive a falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: Put not thy hand with the wicked to be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Witneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Levit. 19.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not go up and down as a Tale-bearer among thy people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 15.3. <hi>He that back-biteth not with his tongue, nor doth evil to his Neighbour, nor taketh up a reproach againſt his Neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 18.8. <hi>The words of a Tale-bearer are as wounds, &amp;c.</hi> 20.10. <hi>Where no Tale-bearer is, the ſtrife ceaſeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jer. 20.10. <hi>I have heard the defamation of many Report, ſay they, and we will report, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to theſe add the Golden Rule, ſo highly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199364:33"/> infringed thereby, Math. 7.12. <hi>Therefore all things whatſoever you would that Men ſhould do unto you, do even ſo unto them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> And would you be ſo dealt with by me and others, ask your own heart? Pray, read Mr. <hi>B.</hi> Rules to this Point, in his <hi>Chriſtian Directory;</hi> ſome of which are given you in <hi>p.</hi> 158. 2. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</hi> And amongſt the reſt, this is one:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If you know it not to be true, or there be no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient evidence to prove it, you are guilty of lying and ſlaundering interpretatively, though it ſhould prove true, becauſe it might have been a lye for ought you know.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, are you not evidently guilty of <hi>Bitter Scoffing</hi> and <hi>Reviling</hi> both Perſon and Book, and notoriouſly guilty of <hi>Railing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As to <hi>Scoffing</hi> and jeering at my Perſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Scoffing and Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Have you not deridingly called me the <hi>Antiſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gnanus,</hi> the <hi>Goliah,</hi> one that is <hi>Philantia nimis inflatus; viz. a proud conceited fellow,</hi> one guilty of notorious <hi>Plagiariſm</hi> or Thievery, and <hi>ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oſcitancy</hi> or heedleſneſs, all in the <hi>Preface of Inf. Bapt.</hi> And ſcoffingly to tell me, <hi>Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus non vidit omnia;</hi> That <hi>I am not ſuch a ſeer as taken to be,</hi> Inf. Bapt. p. 89. A <hi>Hagio-Maſtix, a ſever Laſher,</hi> Ibid. That I am a <hi>Zantippe,</hi> and a <hi>Momus,</hi> a <hi>meer Carper,</hi> Vind. Scoffingly reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Exploits or <hi>Feats done in the daies of my Colonelſhip,</hi> Ibid. p. 93. That you have <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered my Mummery, and pluckt off the mask of my Vizard,</hi> Pref. Vind. and much more of this kind.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to my <hi>Book,</hi> That it is a pompous Piece, very fallacious and contradictious, heapt up with forgeries and prevarications, ſwelled with <hi>Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipedalia
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199364:34"/> verba; viz.</hi> Words of a foot and half long or ridiculous ſtuff, <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> The <hi>non-ſuch,</hi> the Arguments therein <hi>conſiſting only of Trite out-worn things that have been trampled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and confuted again and again,</hi> Pref. Inf. Bapt.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, Whether in a Railing reviling manner you have not called me, <hi>One poſſeſt with a maleveleant Spirit, and filled with envy,</hi> p. 11. Inf. Bapt. <hi>An unworthy Caviler,</hi> p. 13. Ibid. <hi>Of ſo much diſingenuity as to traduce the ſayings of worthy Men,</hi> p. Ibid. <hi>Impudent, ſilly, ridiculous,</hi> p. 16. 2. part. Ibid. <hi>One that will not refuſe the moſt ſordid and ſhameful waies to promote my opinion,</hi> p. 57. Ibid. <hi>A daring Champion;</hi> and again, <hi>A da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Perſon indeed,</hi> p. 72. Ibid. That <hi>I diſcover the ebulition of a malicious Spirit,</hi> p. 106. Ibid. Reflect the <hi>Munſter Venarian Spirit upon me</hi> as one that <hi>is under Satanical deluſion,</hi> p. 99. Ibid. One <hi>that prevaricates to free my ſelf from prevarication,</hi> p. 2. Vind. That <hi>I have added contumacy to my miſtakes,</hi> Pref. Vind. And <hi>that never Writer did more prevaricate and ſhewed more falſhood then I have done,</hi> p. 34. Inf. Bapt.</p>
               <p>But, how ſuch language can ſtand before the following Scriptures? is ſubmitted to your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eph. 4.31. <hi>Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger and clamour, and evill ſpeaking be put away from you with all malice, and be kind one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, tender hearted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 15.1. <hi>A ſoft anſwer turneth away wrath, but grevious words ſtir up anger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tit. 3.2. <hi>Speak evil of no Man;</hi> Tim. 33. <hi>not a brawler;</hi> 1. Cor. 5 10. <hi>If any that is called a Brother be a railer, with ſuch a one do not eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:199364:34"/>
               <p>Matth. 3.22. <hi>Whoſoever is angry with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and whoſoever ſhall ſay unto his brother Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha, ſhall be in danger of the Council: but whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall ſay, Thou fool, ſhall be in danger of Hell fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, I deſire you to conſider whether you are not evidently guilty of <hi>Falſe accuſation,</hi> and notorious falſe <hi>ſpeaking.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, in that general charge, <hi>That never Writer did more prevaricate, or was guilty of more falſhood then my ſelf</hi> (what! none of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Legendaries?) whereas in both your Books you have not been able to make out any one that is ſignificant; for after you have done your utmoſt to make good ſuch a thing, what doth it amount more then to diſcover the miſtaking of 2 or 3 Names, and not rendring that paſſage in <hi>Walden,</hi> ſo much to my advantage as it was, none of which can poſſibly be judged willful miſtakes, nor be truly charged with <hi>forgery</hi> or <hi>prevarication,</hi> which muſt needs therefore return upon you, according to the Rule <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, in thoſe many particular falſhoods you have ſo poſitively charged upon me; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That <hi>I miſrepreſented Dr.</hi> Taylor, <hi>and dealt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully in thoſe Quotations out of his liberty of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, as</hi> p. 35. Inf. Bapt. whereas the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is manifeſt, as p. 51, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of my <hi>Reply.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That <hi>I produced Durandus, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor of Anabaptiſts, as a Witneſs for them,</hi> p. 143. Inf. Bapt. when it is moſt manifeſt I do the quite contrary, p. 242, <hi>Treaty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that I do bring <hi>Jerom,</hi> to ſay <hi>ſuch words upon the</hi> 28. <hi>Matth.; whereas you ſay, they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199364:35"/> are words of my own adding,</hi> and <hi>none of Jeroms; and yet I tell you he ſaith it,</hi> p. 166. Vind. whereas I have made good to you they are <hi>verbatim Jeroms</hi> own words upon that place.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That <hi>I produce Gulielmus</hi> from <hi>the Magdeburgs,</hi> for <hi>ſaying the Virgin Mary ſhould be added to the words of Baptiſm;</hi> which you <hi>ſay is a notorious untruth,</hi> and <hi>that the Magdeburgs ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Virgin Mary,</hi> p. 185 Vind. And which I have expreſly proved, and made good to a tittle as before.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, you accuſe me for abuſing Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> in that Quotation, on the 13. of <hi>John</hi> 10, <hi>making him ſpeak quite otherwiſe then he doth;</hi> Satyricaliy deriding <hi>me for the ſame,</hi> p. 171. of your <hi>Vind.</hi> whereas I have made good to you that I did the Doctor no injury, but quoted his words truly and faithfully.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, You accuſe me, for ſaying, that the <hi>Magdeburgs</hi> ſay, that <hi>the Apoſtles only Baptized the adult or aged,</hi> Ch. 7. p. 2. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> which you ſay is falſe; whereas I ſaid no ſuch thing, as p. 31. of <hi>Reply</hi> is demonſtrated: and though I called for ſatisfaction again and again, yet you in your <hi>Preface</hi> to your Appeal juſtified, your ſelf and ſeverly reprove me for a <hi>tenacious and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Perſon,</hi> for not falling under your charge, what an <hi>evidence it is of my obſtinacy;</hi> whereas my words were only theſe, <hi>That the Magdeburgs tell us, that they find the adult or aged were only Baptized; viz.</hi> in the Scripture Inſtances and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples that they produce: And yet there you have the confidence to <hi>tell me it is alone, nay makes more againſt me;</hi> To which I ſay let it make for or againſt me, that is nothing to the falſhood
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199364:35"/> you fathred upon me, I ſay, none of theſe words, neither doth it make at all againſt me; for they may find Scripture Inſtances only for the adult, and yet believe, as you grant, they did Baptize others then the adult, being two different things; but you tell me the word <hi>[they find only ſuch]</hi> implyed their certainty of the aſſertion, which they were ſo far from believing that they tell us, it appeared from the Apoſtles Writings, that they did not exclude Infants from Baptiſm; and at another time, <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>Vind.</hi> you tell me they ſay that <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> tell us, that Infants were Baptized in the Apoſtles daies; but what then do either of thoſe Inſtances produce any Scripture Example for the Baptizing of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant or any other, but the adult; which ſerves only to evince that had I ſaid, what you would have me ſay I had not ſo fairly repreſented them; <hi>viz.</hi> that they did only Baptize the adult, they believing with you, though upon as little ground, that Baptized the Infants alſo. But in as much as I ſaid they ſaid they found (<hi>viz.</hi> in thoſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Inſtances) Examples only for the one, and not for the other; I faithfully and truly repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, and you did injuriouſly and untruly repreſent me, and for which inſtead of giving me ſatisfaction, you ſtill juſtify your ſelf; and for your better conviction read what I have further ſaid hereof before.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, For your falſe and injurious charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me for producing <hi>Munz'r</hi> and <hi>John of Leyden fro my Witneſſes, to prove againſt Infants Baptiſm,</hi> ſcoffingly telling me, that <hi>you will quietly permit me to enjoy the comfort and honour of ſuch Witneſſes,</hi> p. 154. Vind. whereas I produce them not as any
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199364:36"/> of my Witneſſes, but reflect upon their ſtory, as I tell you <hi>p.</hi> 145. <hi>Reply:</hi> Firſt, to <hi>ſhew the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of charging the Innocent with the crimes of ſuch as are guilty.</hi> And ſecondly, to <hi>Examine that matter of fact, and how proved, upon which ſo much obliquity hath been caſt upon the Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſts, and there way ever ſince;</hi> and both of which I conceive was fairly and modeſtly done by me in that 4. Chapter.</p>
               <p>Eightly, You ſcoffingly tell me, that <hi>my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention will not ſerve me, to ſay any thing againſt one of the Waldenſes Confeſſions for Infants Baptiſm,</hi> viz. <hi>that of Angrogue An.</hi> 1535. viz. As <hi>we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed when we were Baptized, being little ones,</hi> p. 121. <hi>which is a notorious falſhood, for I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſpeak to it,</hi> Treaty p. 310.: And which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he is fain to confeſs, <hi>p.</hi> 122. <hi>Vind.</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Mr. <hi>D.</hi> tells us <hi>p.</hi> 313, that <hi>theſe words being Baptized when little ones were foyſted into the Article,</hi> which I alſo there make good.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Slander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</note>Secondly, You ſo falſly and ſlanderouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> both forreign and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick, that you might the better bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon them, and their cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, as to the Forreign <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> you charge thoſe firſt Commotions, in <hi>Swevia,</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> to be <hi>Anabaptiſtical,</hi> p. 102, <hi>&amp;c</hi> of you Inf. Bapt. the quite contrary upon due Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is <hi>manifeſted,</hi> p. 146 of my Reply, and now unanſwered by you.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the <hi>Anabaptiſts., who were burnt, drowned and ſtarved in Switzerland,</hi> was for <hi>perjury, diſobedience, and ſedition;</hi> and not for <hi>Anabaptiſtry, p.</hi> 79. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> the contrary whereto is fully manifeſted from the Decrees
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199364:36"/> themſelves, which are word for word given you, and by what <hi>Gaſtius</hi> and <hi>Hornberk</hi> ſay in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof; <hi>viz.</hi> for their judgement of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptization,</hi> as appears p. 152 of Rep. and Treat. p. 260. where the Edicts themſelves are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, For charging thoſe in <hi>Germany to be ſo univerſally wicked and immoral,</hi> p. 200. whereas the contrary was made good to you from <hi>Bezas</hi> words, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>many of the Anabaptiſts are good Men, Servants of God, Martyrs of Chriſt;</hi> and our moſt dear <hi>Bn.</hi> in his Ep. to the Gallo-Belgick Churches at <hi>Embden,</hi> as Repl. p. 151. Beſides the account of many 1000 of them that as Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Martyrs ſealed the truth with their Blood, as Treat. 256, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> appears to you.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That <hi>their principles were heretical and blaſphemous,</hi> p. 94. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereas from their confeſſions of Faith themſelves, it is manifeſt they held the ſame with the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears p. 154. Rep.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That the <hi>Miniſts,</hi> thoſe <hi>Holland Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts were for reſiſtance</hi> of <hi>in affinity with the Munſter ſatanical deluſion,</hi> which put <hi>them upon ſuch exorbitances,</hi> p. 99. whereas the quite contrary is ſaid of them, and known to be their conſtant practiſe, refuſing to bear Armes, or to carry ſo much as a Gun in their Ships, as p. 147, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, as to our <hi>Engliſh Anabaptiſts,</hi> have you not in like manner powred reproach upon them, by your notorious falſe accuſations, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, You ſtick not to ſay,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that thoſe who are inclinable to their way, are now grown ſo politick as not to profeſs their Faith till warm weather;</hi> ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199364:37"/> telling us, <hi>that many laſt Summer were dipped in our parts, and in all likelyhood we may hear of many more this Summer,</hi> Preface to Infants Bapt.</p>
               <p>The falſhood and ſlander whereof is refuted by known experience.</p>
               <p>Secondly, neither are you aſhamed to lay <hi>blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>immorality to the charge of diverſe Anabaptiſts in our own Nation,</hi> p. 95. imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I told you in my Reply p. 151. that the reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore with them, otherwiſe, why is it men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as I told you, challinging you to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one Man of thoſe divers Perſons that is truly to be charged with your due proofs for the ſame; or elſe to be eſteemed as truly you ought to be a falſe accuſer of the Brethren, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you have neither done in your laſt <hi>Book,</hi> nor taken ſhame for your ſin and folly therein.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and that above all you have not been affrayed to charge the Principle of <hi>Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſtry</hi> it ſelf, <hi>viz. To be of a dangerous nature:</hi> Your words are theſe, That <hi>you may ſafely affirm that is a Doctrine to be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cted falſe, which is uſually attended with groſs miſcarriages in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it;</hi> for that <hi>beſpeaks it ominous and like a ſpiritual Judgement of God upon it:</hi> And, <hi>I heartily wiſh,</hi> ſay you, <hi>there were no ground to ſay that of ſuch a nature is the Doctrine of Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing grown Perſons, in oppoſition to that of the Inft. Seed of Believers, for not to inſiſt upon.</hi> The <hi>horrid errors and wicked lives of thoſe in Germany, and blaſphemies and immoralities of diverſe in our own Nation.</hi> [that being taken for granted, it ſeems to be undoubted proof in confirmation hereof] And <hi>that as ſome Men hold it (viz.</hi> that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199364:37"/> Baptiſm is a boundary of Communion) <hi>is of ſuch a diſquieting tendancy, that it is not fit for any age or ſtate of the Church.</hi> And as <hi>ſoon as Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Baptiſts</hi> (as they call themſelves, affecting as you ſay that name) <hi>they fall off from Godly Miniſters,</hi> &amp;c as <hi>an effect (as you reflect) of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and pride,</hi> and to the <hi>ſcandal and ſhame of Chriſtian Religion,</hi> p. 94, 95. And in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face you tell us with Mr. <hi>Sydnham,</hi> that <hi>the opinion of</hi> Antipaedobaptiſm <hi>hath been alwaies ominous, and of a wonderful ſtrange influence, to diſtroy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace amongſt Chriſtians, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied alſo with the moſt retinue of errors, ſince the firſt Embrio of it was brought forth, whether by a ſecret judgement of God, or from the natural and ſecret connexion with other Principles of darkneſs, will not with Mr.</hi> Sydnnham <hi>determine</hi> (oh won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Charity!) <hi>only God hath ſhewed ſame black Characters of it in exery Nation, where it hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, <hi>Men of this opinion ſo inflexible, that never any of them was heard to change his opinion, unleſs to ſome worſe error,</hi> (and how can that well be, if this be true that you have affirmed?) But, what can be ſpoken more venanous, more falſe, and repugnant to truth and common ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and more ſavouring of a malicious mind, is left to your Conſcience to determine; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating you ſeriouſly to conſider how ſuch deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can ſtand before theſe following <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Exod. 20 16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>23 1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not receive a falſe report, put not thy hand with the wicked to be an unrighteous witneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199364:38"/>
               <p>It being one of the things the Lord hates and abominates, as viz. Prov. 6.19. <hi>A falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that ſpeaketh lies, and him that ſoweth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 15.18. <hi>He that beareth falſe witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Neighbour is a maul, and a ſword, and and a ſharp Arrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 19.9. <hi>A falſe witneſs ſhall not be unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and he that ſpeaketh lies ſhall not eſcape.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deut. 19, 16, 18. <hi>If a falſe witneſs riſe up againſt any man to teſtify againſt him that which is wrong— the Judges ſhall make diligent ſearch; and behold, if the witneſs be a falſe witneſs, and hath teſtified falſly againſt his Brother, then ſhall you do unto him as he had thought to have done unto his Brother: ſo ſhalt thou put the evil away from among you:</hi> Which I ſhall conclude with that ſerious word, Dr. <hi>Stubs</hi> ſpeaks to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> upon like occaſion, and which I deſire you to lay to heart: <q>If he be a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, who wrongs his Neighbours credit, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by unjuſt raiſing, or upholding an evil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port againſt him, ſurely you have cauſe to lay your hand upon your heart, and to toke ſhame to you ſelf. And if this be the mark of thoſe that ſhall dwell in the Lords Tabernacle, that they are ſuch that neither raiſe nor take up a reproach againſt their Neighbour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15, 3.</q> 
                  <hi>What will become of You</hi> [Mr. Wills] <hi>and where, &amp; with whom muſt you dwell to Eternity, if God do not humble you, for your ſlanderous and lying Tongue and Pen?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication.</note>Fourthly, are you not truly found guilty of <hi>Prevarication,</hi> in many particulars, the thing you ſo notoriouſly and falſly charge upon me, which is according to your own definition, p.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:199364:38"/> 7. Vind. <hi>To coneeal what ought to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared on purpoſe to deceive:</hi> And of which I ſhall give you a few of many Inſtances that might be produced, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Is it not manifeſt, as I have undeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably proved (and in your own word by Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Demonſtration) that you <hi>left out ſo many of the moſt conſiderable paſſages of the Waldenſian Confeſſions,</hi> as p. 45. 2 part Inf. Bapt. and for which you have given no ſatisfaction, though you was ſo earneſtly called upon by my ſelf, as well as Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by leaving out <hi>part of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion you took out of Biſhop <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> p. 119. Vind. which <hi>Hoveden</hi> calls the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> I the <hi>Popiſh Inquiſitors,</hi> you only taking part of it, which declares for <hi>Infant Baptiſm to ſave them;</hi> and yet you can tell us at another time, that the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes</hi> affirmed that it <hi>profited them not for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> That the better to hide the cheat can now tell us in their excuſe, that <hi>this was a dark time</hi> 500 <hi>years ſince; but in the mean time conceal that other part,</hi> which beſpeaks it wholly <hi>Popiſh; viz.</hi> for the <hi>Maſs, Popiſh-Prieſthood, Real preſence, Penance, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> is ſo faithful to give, and which I have at large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> your Partner, in that evil; p. 84. 2 Reply.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by repeating every ſyllable of that <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> p. 169. Vind. called <hi>Calvins;</hi> yet lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out <hi>the laſt Clauſe Eſtius</hi> Annot. on <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. which you know is there, as Treaty p. 176. Vind. And yet ſo often upraid me for not calling it <hi>Eſtius</hi>'s; not only in your firſt Book, but 3 times, and very unmercifully too in your laſt.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:199364:39"/>
               <p>Fourthly, by <hi>Concealing</hi> ſo much of the <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of that out of Calvins Inſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> that you might the better <hi>deceive</hi> your <hi>Engliſh Reader,</hi> and make him believe it was the Objection <hi>of Fools,</hi> and not owned by <hi>Calvin himſelf,</hi> which his next words, as I have demonſtrated and you very well knew, doth.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, by that injurious dealing with me in that Quotation of mine from <hi>Spanhaemius,</hi> and <hi>Oſiander</hi> p. 326. of my Treat you only take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what <hi>Spanhaemius</hi> ſpeaks to part leave out what I ſay <hi>Oſrander ſaith</hi> to the reſt, and reprove me <hi>for my miſtake,</hi> p. 104. <hi>Iuf. Bapt.</hi> and though I called upon you in my <hi>Reply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, for ſatisfaction, Pref. and p.</hi> 148. yet you return ne not one ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable in your laſt.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, by that injurious leaving out what you in your firſt p. quot from <hi>my</hi> 20. <hi>p.</hi> of Reply, which ſpeaks it to be quite an other thing then you make it to be, and thereupon charge me with <hi>prevarication,</hi> if not <hi>madneſs and contradiction,</hi> which was an ill beginning that you ſhould ſo ſtumble at the threfhold; as though I quoted <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and thoſe Antients downwards to prove that the practiſe of <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> was not in thoſe <hi>Centuries,</hi> when I ſay the quite <hi>contrary,</hi> and tell you expreſly that I quote them only for their ſayings, which <hi>ſpeak ſo fully for Adult Baptiſm only,</hi> contrary to their expreſs practiſe. And then by affirming again and again that I contradict my ſelf in owning the Antients were for Infants Baptiſm, and denying there was <hi>Antiquity for it:</hi> whereas the foregoing words in my 19. <hi>p.</hi> enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merates them from <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and not the Antients of the former Centuries, whom I claim for <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers Bapt.</hi> only.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199364:39"/>
               <p>Seventhly, by the like injurious <hi>dealing with me,</hi> p. 57. Vind. taking part of a ſaying of mine in <hi>Treat. p.</hi> 101. and leaving out the next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words in <hi>p.</hi> 102. rendring me thereby ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and then call me at your pleaſure, when I am ſo wholly innocent in the matter; <hi>viz. I juſtify my ſelf in my Reply p.</hi> 36. from <hi>that falſhood you charge upon me, ſuppoſing me to ſay, that dipping was changed into Sprinkling the</hi> 3. <hi>Centurie,</hi> when I only ſay that <hi>the Magdeb. do tell us, that many corruptions about Bapt. was creeping in amongſt the reſt I mentioned</hi> (as I ſaw cauſe) that of <hi>Cyprians</hi> Letter to <hi>Magnus</hi> about <hi>Sprinkling, for dipping.</hi> But withall do ſay, they tell us they do not find any one perſon was then <hi>Baptized</hi> with any of their corrupt Ceremonies, having indeed, as they ſoy, no <hi>authentik proof of the Baptizing of any one perſon;</hi> whereby I ſay it may be <hi>conjectured their corruptions were then more in the notion then pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, which afterwards came all of them to be in uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are pleaſed to repeat my former words about their <hi>beginning to alter the forme from dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin to ſpinkling,</hi> and leave out all my latter words both what I ſo fully ſpeak in the Treat. and my Rep. alſo. And then as p. 51. <hi>I ſuppoſe,</hi> Reader, <hi>thou haſt ſeldom met with the like ridiculous contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in any Author— So that he is the Man that hath cauſe to be aſhamed, and is found very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull in ſpeaking forwards and backwards at his pleaſure; yea, that which is manifeſtly falſe, and then denying in the ſame breath, ſo adding one ſalſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore whilſt you judge me ſo worthy of reproof for <hi>prevarication</hi> (though not at all
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199364:40"/> proved <hi>by you</hi>) and you your ſelf ſo guilty thereof, as ſo fully evidenced, doth not this following Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture concern you?</p>
               <p>Rom. 2.1.23. <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable, O Man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt, for wherein thou judgeſt thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doth the ſame thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>we are ſure the judgement of God is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to truth againſt them, which commit ſuch things. And thinkeſt thou this, O Man, that judges them, which do ſuch things and doth the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgement of God,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſe 21. <hi>Thou therefore which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf, thou that preacheſt, a Man ſhould not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal.</hi> So thou that teacheſt a Man ſhould not prevaricate, why art thou guilty of ſo much prevarication, and ſo ſelf judged and condemned therein?</p>
               <p>And fifthly, is it not evident that you are hanouſly guilty of <hi>Forgery;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. <hi>Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> pretending Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſay <hi>ſo</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> when they ſay no ſuch thing, or the quite <hi>contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which I ſhall give you few Inſtances.</p>
               <p>Firſt, do not you affirm <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>Vind. that Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſheweth from Wickliffs works that he was for Infants Baptiſm;</hi> whereas he abundantly ſaith the quite contrary, and your own Pen is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained at another time to acknowledge, as <hi>p.</hi> 125, 172. <hi>Vind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, do not you poſitively <hi>affirme, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Auſtin ſaith in bis third Book</hi> De Anima, <hi>c.</hi> 13. that <hi>Vincentius Victor his opinion was that Infants that dyed Baptized went immediately to Heaven;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is no ſuch thing ſaid, either in that or any other Chapter that I can find.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:199364:40"/>
               <p>Thirdly, do not you ſay that <hi>Rainerius in the Catalogue of the Waldenſian errours brings not one word of their denying Inf. Bapt.</hi> as p. 67. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> whereas he expreſly ſaith in that Catalogue, that <hi>they affirmed Inf. Bapt.</hi> was nothing worth, and that <hi>Goſſips that undertook for them knew not what they did; for which ſee Rep.</hi> p. 125.131.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, do now affirme that Dr. <hi>Taylor in his Book called Conſideration of the Practiſe of the Church,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hamond in his Letter of Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, had given anſwer to thoſe Arguments produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by me, out of his Liberty of Prophecy againſt Infants Baptiſm,</hi> as p. 36, 37, 98 of your <hi>Infants Baptiſm;</hi> whereas in p. 53, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of my <hi>Reply,</hi> it is fully made out from both their words, that they do confirme thoſe Arguments to be good that are therein brought againſt the principle Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, the <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> bring for that their pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, do not <hi>you prodvce</hi> Baſil, <hi>to be an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent wotneſs for Infants Baptiſm in the fourth Century, as p.</hi> 136. Whereas there is never <hi>ſuch a word to be found in any of Baſils writings that doth yet appear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, you do poſitively affirme from the acquaintance you had with Father <hi>Baſil</hi> that he in his third Book Contr. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nomiam</hi> in the very next lines after thoſe words <hi>I had repeated of that quotation, declared himſelf to be for Infants Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm.</hi> And for <hi>my omitting the ſame, call upon the Reader to have a ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e henceforwards how they tru t my quotations f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r the palpable abuſe done to that Father, and for a fallacy and falſhood upon the Reader,</hi> p. 13. Inf. Bapt. And again in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, charging me <hi>for curtailing and leaving out
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199364:41"/> part of that Sentence of Baſils.</hi> About which I got a Friend firſt to write to you, to know where to find it: to which you replyed, that<note n="*" place="margin">You char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me not for miſquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and miſapply- it, but could not direct to the page.</note> for which manifeſt injury done to <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>me,</hi> alſo in that your ſevere <hi>Reflection,</hi> I called for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as p. 48. <hi>Reply.</hi> But all that I can get yet from you is this, that you miſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k only a name <hi>Baſil</hi> for <hi>Naziazen,</hi> p. 61. <hi>Vind.</hi> Equilizing my miſtake of <hi>Albertus</hi> for <hi>Aquinus with it,</hi> p. 183.</p>
               <p>Which I cannot take for due pay: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not a bare ſlip in haſte, but a thing juſtified by you in coold blood when I gave you time to <hi>deliberate upon it,</hi> by ſending ſo civily <hi>to you that</hi> you might have an opportunity to rectify it, or clear your ſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by your extenuating it, as though it was juſt <hi>like my miſtaking, Albertus</hi> for <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi> which I can by no means admit for that was a <hi>quotation</hi> for you to prove for Infant Bapt. which cannot demonſtrate any <hi>wilfulneſs in me;</hi> nor that I could have any end in the miſtake, nor was it improved to <hi>your prejudice;</hi> whereas that of yours was a great <hi>proof againſt me,</hi> highly boaſted of by you to diſcover your reading and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with that <hi>Father,</hi> and improved much to my diſgrace, and often and very ſeverly incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated upon me. Therefore I do expect from you more fuller ſatisfaction therein, and your due humiliation <hi>for ſuch a notorious miſcarriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As well for your vainglorious boaſt as your tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling <hi>ſo upon me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, in like manner was your dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling about what you own to be your miſtake, only of a Century <hi>reſpectiong Peter Bruis p.</hi> 53. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> out of <hi>Oſiander,</hi> which was not only ſo, but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199364:41"/> the ſever laſhes you gave <hi>me about it; viz.</hi> That <hi>you ſee by this that when Men are ingaged in a Cauſe, and wedded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o an opinion, they will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the moſt ſordid and ſhamefull waies to promote it fall in with ſlanderous Papiſts, and take up what they ſay to defend their opinions, witneſs my Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt.</hi> And at this rate you go on chaſtiſing of me, and all upon your own groſs <hi>forgery and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake:</hi> For which Sir, I expect your <hi>repentance,</hi> you did not miſtake a Century only, but <hi>Chriſtianity, Civility,</hi> and <hi>Common Honeſty</hi> alſo; and you did not only <hi>abuſe me,</hi> but <hi>Oſiander Cluniacenſis, Peter Bruis,</hi> and yet have you the confidence to tell me <hi>p.</hi> 131. that you could retort upon me, that I belyed <hi>Calvin,</hi> I belyed <hi>the Truth,</hi> and by that <hi>forgery,</hi> I would <hi>cover,</hi> and <hi>hide,</hi> and <hi>abuſe</hi> the World with a <hi>cheat,</hi> and <hi>much more, my own Conſcience,</hi> by that piece of <hi>folly and falſhood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas is now manifeſtly appears that I did put <hi>Eſtius</hi> his name to the Quotation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there could be neither cheat, abuſing of the World, forgery, nor falſhood in the matter; which doth but heighten your crime, and makes more work <hi>for Repentance,</hi> which I alſo duly call far from you.</p>
               <p>And therefore to further, the ſame deſire you to read and conſider the following Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Lev. 19.11. <hi>Ye ſhall not lie one to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 14.5. <hi>A faithful witneſs will not lie, but a falſe witneſs uttereth lies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eph. 4.25. <hi>Wherefore puting away lying ſpeak every Man truth with his Neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Col. 39. <hi>Lye not one to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſalm. 119.69. <hi>The proud hath forged lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jer. 9, 3. <hi>They bend their tongues like bows for lies, but are not valiant for the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:199364:42"/>
               <p>With the Scriptures before mentioned, Rom. 2.1, 2, 3, 21. <hi>Becauſe you have proclamed me ſuch a forger, and judged me for the ſame, but has yet made no proof thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſixthly, are not you guilty of <hi>Miſtranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">6. <hi>Miſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Miſrendring Authors.</hi> For <hi>Inſtance;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That notorious paſſage about the <hi>Miniſts,</hi> which you tranſlate quite contrary to <hi>Truth; viz.</hi> that <hi>they were for Reſiſtance in the Munſter way, and for diſtroying the wicked by force of Armes, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the ſetting up the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> p. 99. of Inf. Bapt. when the quite contrary is there ſaid and the conſtant knowledge of their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and practiſe evinceth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for Miſrendring that paſſage out of <hi>Calvins Inſtitutes,</hi> before accounted for in the appeal to be the objection of fools, when <hi>Calvin</hi> owns the ſame to be his Judgement.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, for Miſrendring a paſſage out of <hi>Auſtins</hi> 3. <hi>B. de Anima,</hi> fathring that upon <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Victor,</hi> that is not there ſaid of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourthly, for tranſlating <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſignify only an Infant without underſtanding, p. 11. <hi>Inf. Bapt.</hi> when the contrary is true, as appears 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>Thou haſt known the holy Scriptures a Child, there is the ſame word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, whether your ſolemn Appeal to the <hi>Searcher of hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">7. <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy.</hi>
                  </note> that you have no malignity to my Perſon, having ground to hope I am a Godly Man; and in your Preface to <hi>Vind. that you love me as a Brother though erring, and had much rather convince then ſhame me, can be well reconciled to ſincerity, and not rather ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſy:</hi> when it is conſidered, Firſt, how you have declined all fair Brotherly waies
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199364:42"/> of receiving ſatisfaction, chooſing rather in this publick manner to <hi>reproach</hi> and <hi>ſlander me</hi> upon hear-ſay: 2. Jeer and <hi>Scoff at me:</hi> 3. to <hi>Raile</hi> upon and <hi>Revile me</hi> in that unchriſtian manner you have done, ſpeaking ſo much <hi>evil of me falſly:</hi> 4. proclaiming me with your <hi>Aſſociates</hi> in the <hi>Gazette</hi> and in the <hi>Catalogues</hi> (where you know I cannot follow you for my vindication) 5. And at laſt ſo groundleſly, diſorderly, not to ſay maliciouſly, to Appeal to the <hi>Baptiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> againſt me, as a perſon that has added contumacy to my miſtakes and evils.</p>
               <p>All which is recommended to your Conſcience in the ſight of God, (and all that are conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enciouſly concerned with you) leaving it to your choice, which of your promiſes you will keep, whether that in the concluſion of your firſt <hi>Pref. Vind. To anſwer me by ſilence, becauſe you will not gape againſt an Oven:</hi> Or that in the end of your laſt <hi>Preface,</hi> viz. <hi>That if I can make it appear that you have wronged me herein, as you can truly ſay you did it not willingly: So you faithfully promiſe to make me publick ſatisfaction, by acknowledging your miſtakes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:43"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 8. l. ult. r. <hi>enjoyned,</hi> p. 10. l. 28. r. <hi>Rhenanus,</hi> p. 14. l. 32. r. <hi>obloquy,</hi> p. 18. l. 13. dele <hi>rhe,</hi> and the <hi>Comma</hi> at Doctor, l. 23. r. <hi>to</hi> ſpeak, l. 26. r. <hi>words,</hi> p. 19. l. 28. r. <hi>by</hi> them, p, 21, l, 15, dele <hi>that,</hi> p. 35. l. 27 r. <hi>ought</hi> ſo to do, p. 38 l. 1. r. <hi>codice,</hi> p. 41. l. 16 &amp; 19. r. <hi>Aquinas,</hi> p, 51, l, 19, r, <hi>philautia,</hi> p. 52. l. 8, r, <hi>malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> l, 17, r. <hi>Munſter and,</hi> p, 55, l, 21, r, <hi>that</hi> they, l, 32, r, <hi>for,</hi> p. 65. l. 23. dele <hi>of,</hi> p, 67, l, 19, r, <hi>every,</hi> l, 25, r, <hi>venemous,</hi> p, 70, l, 12, r, <hi>Oſiander,</hi> p. 73. l. 8. for <hi>do now</hi> r. do not you, l. 27. r. <hi>Eunomium.</hi> p, 74, l, 8, r, <hi>Nazianzen, equalizing,</hi> l, 9, and 18, r, <hi>Aquinas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire the Reader, where I mention to Mr. <hi>Will's</hi> (in p, 2, <hi>Pref.</hi> and p. 51, &amp; 53,) the miſtakes I own, not to underſtand it excluſive of thoſe few ſlight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material ones not mentioned there, as that of the Canon of <hi>Conſtant,</hi> which I my ſelf found to be ſpurious, that of <hi>Chryſoſtom's</hi> not being in a different Character, my tranſlating the paſſage of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> metaphraſtically, putting <hi>Zonaras</hi> for the <hi>Magdeburgs;</hi> that of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, work,</hi> for <hi>be</hi> no ſuch cauſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:199364:43"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT by <hi>H. D.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOR the Readers better and more full ſatisfaction (after the great cry againſt me for <hi>Forgery</hi> and <hi>prevarication</hi> by my <hi>Antagoniſts</hi>) I have here gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you together, this brief account of all the miſtakes of moment that I have met with from any hand. And which the Reader is deſired to correct in the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> as he meets with them; which are as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Of my own or Friends diſcovery, <hi>p. 55, 56. for Eaſtern r. Weſtern, p. 139. for</hi> Eraſmus <hi>r.</hi> Beza, <hi>p. 124. dele what is produced from</hi> Lanafrank <hi>about</hi> Beringarius, <hi>and p. 68. and 115. and Index, dele the Canon of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of</hi> Conſtant. <hi>as ſpurious.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2. Of Mr.</hi> Baxters <hi>finding out, p. 223. for 3 &amp; 4 book againſt the</hi> Donatiſts <hi>r. 4 book, p. 286. 294. for</hi> Cochleus <hi>r.</hi> Walden.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Of Mr.</hi> Wills's, <hi>p. 75. for</hi> Aquinas <hi>r.</hi> Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, <hi>p. 116. dele</hi> Deodans, <hi>and for</hi> Hincmarus <hi>r.</hi> Sericius, <hi>p. 117. r.</hi> Magdeburgs <hi>for</hi> Zonaras, <hi>p. 155. for</hi> work no ſuch cauſe <hi>r.</hi> be no ſuch cauſe, <hi>p. 287. dele</hi> Pelagius <hi>and</hi> Vincentius Victor.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe being all the errors of any weight I have yet met with from any: The judicious Reader will be more able to diſcern;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:199364:44"/>
               <hi>1.</hi> Whether here be any <hi>Forgery</hi> or <hi>Prevaricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or any wilful <hi>abuſe,</hi> or <hi>miſleading</hi> the Reader, (as with ſo much virulence ſuggeſted) or any other over-ſight or miſtakes, then ſuch as uſually attend other writings; and therefore whether all the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and out-cry of my Antagoniſts, diſcovers not more of <hi>malice</hi> then <hi>matter,</hi> and is the reſult rather of <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>paſſion,</hi> then a <hi>zeal</hi> for the candid inveſtigation of truth.<note n="*" place="margin">To lead from the main que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to things not to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and make a hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vy ſtir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, is the right Method of Cavillers; and which my Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites take with me in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Whether ſince the Exceptions appear to be ſo <hi>inſignificant</hi> and <hi>immaterial</hi> to the great point contended about, and no weightyer objections made good after ſo ſevere a ſcrutiny, and troubling the World with the duſt and pudder made about them, the Queſtion in debate be not fully given up, viz. <hi>That it is now clearly manifeſt, that there is no Primitive Antiquity for Infants Baptiſm, nor no Record to make it appear that it was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as Chriſts Ordinance for the firſt 300 years;</hi> The truth whereof having not only been evinced by unanſwered Arguments and Demonſtration; but from their own Pens, being conſtrained at laſt to acknowledge, <hi>That except in caſe of danger of Death, there is no Record in the Hiſtory of the Church for the neceſſity thereof in thoſe firſt times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Reader is deſired to take notice what <hi>ground</hi> we get herein, and how far this <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration</hi> tends to juſtifie our practice, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That the Baptizing of Believers, after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, is not only evidenced by expreſs precept and example from the Scripture; (the true and only way whereby Chriſts Ordinances are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht to Proteſtants) but by the univerſal conſent of all Ages; our very <hi>Enemies</hi> being <hi>Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:199364:44"/>
               <hi>2.</hi> That the Baptizing of Infants is neither to be made good by any <hi>expreſs precept</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> from Scripture; nor as an <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition</hi> for theſe firſt and pureſt times; as our Adverſaries alſo acknowledge; though they would inſinuate as if they could conſequentially deduce it; whereas no natural nor un-forc'd conſequence can be inferr'd in its favour from Scripture or primitive Antiquity, but abſurd and illogical <hi>non-ſequiturs,</hi> proving nothing ſo much as the weakneſs of the cauſe they endeavour to ſupport.</p>
            <p>So that it neceſſarily and undeniably follows, That though <hi>Papiſts</hi> and ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> may plead <hi>Antiquity</hi> ſince the 5th. <hi>Century,</hi> and no higher (the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Synod that firſt impoſed it, being in the year <hi>416.</hi>) for the neceſſity of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Children to <hi>take away Original ſin, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> and <hi>ſave their Souls,</hi> with the Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitants of <hi>Chryſm, Exorciſm, Goſſips,</hi> &amp;c. Yet the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> with whom we have to do <hi>(owning this to be a poyſonous Antichriſtian Doctrine)</hi> cannot pretend higher for their Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Children upon the account of <hi>foederal</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral right is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Mr. <hi>Ed. Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinſon.</hi>
               </note> right then the 15th. or 16th. Century. And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (they rejecting the grounds of the Ancients) their Infants Baptiſm upon this new <hi>Medium</hi> is a very <hi>novelty.</hi> So that I hope we ſhall hear no more of Antiquity for Infants Baptiſm of any ſort.</p>
            <p>And 3ly, that it yet undeniably appears, that a famous Witneſs has been born for <hi>Believers</hi> and againſt <hi>Infants Baptiſm</hi> in the ſucceſſive Ages ſince Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And as a further ratification of the truth of theſe things pleaded for betwixt us in this conteſt, it may not be unneceſſary to mind the Reader the ſenſe
<pb facs="tcp:199364:45"/> that ſome <hi>ſtanders</hi> by have given by their <hi>ſuffrages,</hi> both as to the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>matter</hi> pleaded for, which you have exemplified in the learned and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>us diſquiſitions of Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> in his late <hi>Reflections</hi> and <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> and <hi>Whiſton's</hi> Writings. The Letter of Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> the Epiſtle of Mr. <hi>Tho. DeLaune</hi> before Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon's;</hi> all of them ſo great ſtrangers to me, that I neither ever ſaw any of their <hi>Faces,</hi> or ſo much as heard of their <hi>names</hi> that I know of, before their ſaid <hi>works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to which I may preſume to add a Let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſent to me upon this occaſion, <hi>by a perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> a ſearcher into this Controverſie, and one of known <hi>worth, ability,</hi> and <hi>moderation;</hi> which you may take as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>As to Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Piece (which ſo ſoon as I heard of, I forthwith ſent for) I have curſorily run over, eſpecially that part thereof, which more immediately concerns your ſelf, and am ſorry to ſee ſo much <hi>Rancor</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> in the writings of one who hath had ſo great a Name for <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Piety:</hi> But whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not <hi>Pride, Paſſion,</hi> and an <hi>Over-weening Opinion</hi> of a mans ſelf carry thoſe who are over come by them?</p>
                  <p>When I firſt read your <hi>Treatiſe of Baptiſm,</hi> I hoped it would have occaſioned a <hi>ſerious</hi> and <hi>full Diſquiſition</hi> of that point; but whether through the <hi>unhappy</hi> temper of your <hi>Opponents,</hi> or what elſe I know not, I have been hitherto <hi>diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in my <hi>expectation,</hi> meeting in their writings
<pb facs="tcp:199364:45"/> with more of <hi>heat, paſſion,</hi> and <hi>perſonal reflections,</hi> then of <hi>Reaſon</hi> or a <hi>ſober Inquiſition</hi> after Truth.</p>
                  <p>I am not ſo well vers'd in <hi>Antiquity,</hi> as to ſay when <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> firſt came in uſe amongſt <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but admire a matter of <hi>fact</hi> only, as that is, ſhould be ſo difficult to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: But if it were not in all, or at leaſt the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>pureſt</hi> Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> (as ſome learned <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> ſeem to grant it was not) it cannot be ſaid to be of <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition;</hi> the beſt plea, if true, I have yet heard for it; and therefore I could wiſh that Point had been <hi>ſoberly</hi> and <hi>calmly</hi> debated. I muſt confeſs, I know not of any <hi>difference</hi> amongſt <hi>Profeſsors</hi> of more <hi>unhappy</hi> and <hi>pernicious</hi> Conſequence than this of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in regard of that <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Diviſion</hi> it cauſes amongſt <hi>Learned,</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and truly Pious Chriſtians; for ſuch I no ways doubt but there are of both perſwaſions. But 'tis matter of greateſt trouble and ſorrow to me, to ſee with what <hi>uncharitable</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Spirits</hi> ſome men manage this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, even to the reproach and ſcandal of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and this too in a day, when our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſufferings ought in prudence, if not for Piety-ſake to unite us; at leaſt in <hi>Brotherly</hi> love, and a Chriſtian Walking together ſo far as we have <hi>attained,</hi> and in other things to a Patient waiting for the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the mind of God, to them that differ; who in his good timewill, I doubt not, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite</hi> our <hi>Affections, Heal</hi> our <hi>Breaches,</hi> and make us <hi>all</hi> but <hi>one Sheep-fold,</hi> under the great Shepherd of the Sheep <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> to whoſe guidance and protection I moſt heartily recommend you, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:199364:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And laſtly, I hope the</hi> Baptiſts <hi>anſwer to Mr.</hi> Wills <hi>his</hi> Appeal <hi>againſt me, will have no ſmall tendency to iſsue this Controverſie, whoſe diligent ſearch (by thoſe learned Men they appointed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) into the Authors quoted by me, and excepted againſt by him, will be a ſufficient vindication (I doubt not) of my</hi> integrity <hi>in my</hi> Quotations, <hi>as well as the truth aſſerted thereby; and a due Reproof to Mr.</hi> Wills <hi>for his great</hi> Temerity, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf ſo eminently found guilty by them in ſo many things he ſo injuriouſly charges upon me, inſomuch that they (as he deſires,</hi> in caſe my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency appears to them) <hi>as you ſee, have thought juſt to acquit me, and reflect the blame of the Charge upon himſelf: All which is again ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Conſcience, the Impartial Readers, and the bleſſing of the Almighty. By</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>H. D.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
